<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The summe of christianitie gatheryd out almoste of al placis of scripture, by that noble and famouse clerke Francis Lambert of Auynyon. And translatyd, and put in to prynte in Englyshe, by Tristram Reuel. The yere of our lorde. 1536</title>
            <title>Farrago omnium fere rerum theologicarum. English</title>
            <author>Lambert, Franz, 1486-1530.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1536</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 188 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 83 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A05035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15179</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109321</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844971</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844971</idno>
            <idno type="VID">9830</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A05035)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 9830)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 134:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The summe of christianitie gatheryd out almoste of al placis of scripture, by that noble and famouse clerke Francis Lambert of Auynyon. And translatyd, and put in to prynte in Englyshe, by Tristram Reuel. The yere of our lorde. 1536</title>
                  <title>Farrago omnium fere rerum theologicarum. English</title>
                  <author>Lambert, Franz, 1486-1530.</author>
                  <author>Revel, Tristram.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24], 22, 22-31, 31-59 [ie. 56] leaves : ill. (woodcut)  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Redman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1536]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Farrago omnium fere rerum theologicarum.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Leaf 56 misnumbered 59.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Korey Jackson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:9830:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:9830:1"/>
            <p>The ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of chriſtianitie gatheryd out almoſte of al placis of ſcripture, by that noble and famouſe clerke <hi>FRANCIS LAM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BERT</hi> of Auynyon.</p>
            <p>And tranſlatyd, and put in to prynte in Englyſhe, <hi>by TRISTRAM REVEL.</hi> The yere of our lorde.</p>
            <p>1536. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:9830:2"/>
            <head>The table of this boke.</head>
            <p>FYrſte ther is an epiſtle of the tran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlatour to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt vertuous Quene <hi>ANNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is alſo the epyſtle of the Author in place or ſtede of a prologe. to the moſte noble lorde, lorde Seba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyan prynce of Lauſane, in the which is made anſwere to thoſe thyngꝭ that Tregaryus wrytte to the ſame Lorde in hys epyſtle prefyxed, hys hundreth paradoxes.</p>
            <p>Alſo theſe thynges folowynge be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated vpon in .385. paradoxes or queſtyons, deuyded into chapiters.</p>
            <list>
               <item>¶ The fyrſt Chapiter of the blydnes of the worldes paſte and hathe Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes .29.</item>
               <item>¶ The ſeconde Chapiter of the holy Churche of god and reprouable ſyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goge of Sathan of canonyzynge and inuocatyon of Saynctes and hathe Paradoxes .31.</item>
               <item>¶ The thyrde Chapiter of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munyon of Sayntes, of excomunyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon and bulles of the ſonne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyon
<pb facs="tcp:9830:2"/>
and hathe Paradoxes .14.</item>
               <item>¶ The fourthe Chapitre of true good workes and the lawe of grace, and the goſpell, and vertues of the faythefull, and hathe Paradoxes .20.</item>
               <item>¶ The fyfthe Chapitre of the preſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode of the faythefull, and true mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres of the churche .i. byſhopes and deacons, and hathe Paradoxes .38.</item>
               <item>¶ The ſyxte Chapitre of punyſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and depoſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g falſe byſhopes, and falſe apoſtles, and hathe Paradoxes .31.</item>
               <item>¶The ſeuenthe Chapitre of the auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toryty and miniſtery of byſhopes, and in what thynges they ought to be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte to prynces, and rulers, &amp; of ſanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuaryes, and hathe Paradoxes .27.</item>
               <item>¶ The eyght Chapitre that byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes maye nat be prynces and lordes, and hathe Paradoxes .13.</item>
               <item>¶ The nynthe Chapitre of abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of fyrſte frutes tythes and offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynges, and what the faythfull owe to theyr byſſhoppes .i. miniſters of the worde, alſo of thoſe thinges that they owe to prynces and rulers, and hathe Paradoxes .28.</item>
               <item>¶ The tenthe Chapitre of the table
<pb facs="tcp:9830:3"/>
of the lorde and execrable coſtomes of the kyngdome of the ſon of perdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, vtterly to be extincte and putte downe and of Purgatory, and hathe Paradoxes .36.</item>
               <item>¶ The eleuenthe Chapitre of ſectes and beggyng, &amp; hathe Paradoxes .18.</item>
               <item>¶The twelfthe Chapitre to whom it belongythe to iudge of doctryne if it be of god or nat and of wycked vniuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſyties, and hathe Paradoxes .15.</item>
               <item>¶ The thyrtenthe Chapitre of the partes (as they call it) of penaunce and all that belongythe there to, and hathe Paradoxes .85.</item>
            </list>
            <p>¶ This terme Paradoxe is a concluſyon or poſiſcyon or queſtyon. ☞:<g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>:☜ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9830:3"/>
            <head>The epyſtle of the tranſlator</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the moſte gracyous Quene <hi>ANNE,</hi> moſt deare wyfe, of our moſt drade ſoueraygne lorde, <hi>HENRY</hi> the eyght of Englande, &amp; of Frau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce kynge, defender of the faythe, and lorde of Irelande, and vnder god, next, chefe, and ſupreme heade of the churche of Englande, your moſt bonde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tour Tryſtram Reuel wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhethe helthe.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Race, and peace, from God the father, and the lorde Ieſus Chryſte, be with you moſte Gracy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Quene / moſte hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, and with all reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence gyuynge laudes / and prayſynges vnto almyghtye god for your grace, euen after the mynde of ſaynte Paule,<note place="margin">Ephe</note> alwayes in all my prayers for your grace, with gladnes, bycauſe of the felyſhype whiche your grace hathe in the goſpel, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fyrſt day vntyll nowe, and am ſurely certy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, that he whiche hathe begonne a good worke in you, wyl alſo go forthe
<pb facs="tcp:9830:4"/>
with it, vntyl the day of Ieſus chryſt, with the encreaſe and eſtablyſhement of his goſpell, as yet but yonge &amp; hath many enemyes, to whome the lorde ſende the day of his viſytatyon, to hꝭ honoure and glory, and your grace to perſeuere, with all dylygence as your grace haue begone to promote, furder, and ſette forthe,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 1.</note> Goddes worde, vpon the ſelfe ſame zele that ſaynte Iohan cryed in deſerte, make redy the way of the lorde / So that euery man may be rulyd by the laſte wyll, and teſtamente of our eldeſt brother, and lorde Ieſus Chryſte, which is ſuffycyent for al vs to lyue after, to euerlaſtynge helth, to knowe God y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father to be God alone and who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath ſent Ieſus Chryſte,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> without any other foreyne or ſtraung lawes, he hath alſo ſtraytly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded his lawyers,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>odi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> byſhopes ouer the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation or any other, nether to adde or dymynyſhe one Iote, to, or from hys forſayd laſt wyl,<note place="margin">iſai. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſayng, I am thy god, the God of Zelotes, one alone ſuffy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyent, thou ſhalte haue no ſtraunge godes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my ſyht,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie. 31.</note> nether turne to the ryght hande, nor the lefte. And nowe
<pb facs="tcp:9830:4"/>
heare Iſrael the preceptes, and iudge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentes, whiche I teache the, that do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge them, thou mayſte lyue, &amp; goinge in, may poſſeſſe the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de that the lorde God of thy fathers wyll gyue the. Thou ſhalt adde nothyng to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I ſpeake to the,<note place="margin">Deu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> nor take any thynge from it, kepe the commaundementes of thy lord god, and holde the kynges hyghe waye, the pathe of holy ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which is the worde, beſydes who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is none other, furthermore vpon the ſelfe ſame charge, he hathe orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, inſtytute, and made executors for the performaunce of hys ſayde teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without reſpecte of perſon, ſhulde be equally receyued, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of ſundry wyſe. Fyrſt he hathe inſtytute,<note place="margin">Mark 17. Math 16. Mark 10. Lu. 2. Hu. 1 3. Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gum. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Byſſhoppes to teache hys people therin to loſe, to bynde, to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce grace, and remiſſyon of ſynnes, gyuen thoroughe hys worde. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer he hathe put kynges, prynces, &amp; rulers, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr auctorytes, to punyſhe, correcte and expulſe from hys congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacyon, tranſgreſſours of hys lawes, and ſtraungers, not ſekynge to edefye but to kyl, which be callyd bloude ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:5"/>
men lyuynge after theyr owne braynes, and fantaſies, not commynge in at the dore but another waye, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tynge forthe theyr owne lawes &amp; tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyons, almoſt deceyuynge the very electe, as is wel knowen to the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, with ſuppreſſyon and treadynge vnder fote,<note place="margin">Math. 4.</note> euen to this day, the lyght of euerlaſtyng veryte, the lyuely word of god. And for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe moſt chryſten Quene, that noble and famous clarke <hi>FRAVNCYS' LAMBERT</hi> Author of thys lytle treatyſe, percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge both the exilynge of the goſpel from chryſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes hartes,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 16</note> and alſo the ruyne, and deſtructyon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, moſte lyke a true champyon hath ſette forthe, to the quycke Image the peſtylente doctryne, and actes of the kyngedome of perdycyon, the church of Antychryſte, the men of ſynne, the Pope, and his ſectes, in many workes with great laboures and ſtudy, chefly in thys lytle boke, clerely confutynge the ſynagoge of Sathan as a noble executour of his brothers aforeſayde wyll, and by the ſame auctoryte hathe deſcrybed and ſet forth true myniſters
<pb facs="tcp:9830:5"/>
of goddes moſte holye worde, a boke to be redde of all chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people, therin they may learne to walke in theyr cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, pryncypally byſhopes ouer the congregacion, which ſayde lytle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe by a good chriſten brother lent to me, as yet bothe yonge in yeres, and muche leſſe in learnynge, haue taken in hande to tranſlate this ſo precyous a treaſure, and offer it to your moſt no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble grace rudely ſette forth, truſtynge that youre grace wyll cauſe the ſame, eloquently and ornatly to be tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by ſome of your dyſcret, wyſe, and well learned clarkes, moſt humbly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſechynge your grace, in good parte to take this my rude enterpryſe, pryncy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally (to confeſſe the truthe) bycauſe I am very vnmete to do ſuch a thinge and partly for lake of tyme, oppreſſed with pouertye, the whiche (as the Poete <hi>MANTVANE</hi> wrytteth) is enemy to good maners, conſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye my wryttynge is verye courſe and baſe, as yet ferre from the trade of a wryter, the which be the cauſes of my offerynge to your grace, ſo rude a vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, ſo indygeſte a phraſe, and to be
<pb facs="tcp:9830:6"/>
brefe, ſo vnſemely ſet together, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I humbly beſeche your grace, to take theſe my fyrſte frutꝭ (yf they may be called frutes) euen as Chryſte our mayſter hathe accepted the offerynge of the pore woman whoſe wyll was good,<note place="margin">Mar. 12</note> 
               <note place="margin">Lu. 21.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe offered al that ſhe hade thoughe it was but lytle. And the holy goſte preſerue our ſayde ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraygne Lorde, and your moſt deare huſbande, your grace, &amp; the ladye <hi>ELEZA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BETHE</hi> Prynceſſe, Doughter, &amp; heyre vnto you bothe, and gyue to you the lyght of hys mercye, to whome, with god the Father, and the Sonne, be honoure, and glorye for euer more. So be it. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:9830:6"/>
            <head>The epyſtell of the auctour.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> To the noble, and moſte gentyll lorde: lorde <hi>SEBASTIAN,</hi> of Mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t faulcone, prynce of Lauſanc.</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>FRAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIS LAMBERT</hi> the vnprofytable ſeruancte of Ieſus Chriſte,</signed>
               <salute>grace, and peace, of god the father, and the lorde Ieſus Chriſte.<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ot many yeres paſſyd, moſte noble prynce, wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I ſhulde preache the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re, and holſome, worde of god, at your cytie of Lauſane. I dyd ꝑceiue, by many argumentes, bothe the ſobre gentylnes of youre mynde, and alſo the outragyous wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kednes, of certayne flaterers, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuers. For at altymes, where as you were preſent, at my ſermons, you dyd moſte purely fauer the worde of god, and whan you were conſtreynyd, with vrgent buſynes, to be abſent (whiche was ones, and eftſones) as you haue enformyd me, very many were aboute ſumwhat buſyly, to alyenat, or make
<pb facs="tcp:9830:7"/>
you ſtraunge, ye as it were to ſay, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiouſly to drawe you frome the worde of god. lyke fyrye burnyng knyghtes, adfyrmyng that I preachyd hereſye. But at the laſte the myghty verytye, hathe ſo conuycte you, that you haue wryten many thynges for me, and I gladly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, that for the loue of you I was gentylly enterteynyd, with the Berne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes, Ligurynes, Baſylyanes, &amp; Friburgyanes. Farthermore, at my de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>partyng from you, you inſtantly deſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryd me, very ofte to wryte to you, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che to do I gladly promyſed, in tyme conuenient. wherfore I beſeche your hyghnes of pardone, bycauſe I haue nat performyd it to thys daye, for it chanſyd nother by obliuiouſnes, or ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>glygence, but very ofte, whan I was about to do it, I was conſtreynydly rapte, to other maters. The laſte of al I wolde haue made anſwere, to the hundreth paradoxes, or queſtyones, of <hi>CONRADVS TREGARIVS</hi> the Auguſtyne frereſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to you. wherin he is very buſy, not alonly to pull you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way frome Chriſte, but alſo the noble gentyles of Heluetia. although he do
<pb facs="tcp:9830:7"/>
glory, with pretens and zele of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite of Chriſt, in the ſpirite of erroure and blyndnes. Veryly he dothe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che nothyng leſſe then Chriſt. For he laboryth very ſore, to vndermyne the vyneyarde of the lorde of companies. that is to ſaye, the congregacyon or churche of chriſten people, euyn lyke to a crafty or wyly foxe. but this foxe, muſte be taken, I ſaye thys lytle foxe, ye the whiche is without effycacytie, or ſtrengthe of the ſpirite, that other he maye be ſauyd, or els confoundyd put downe. accordynge as the ſpouſe commaundyth in the cantykles, ſaing take to vs theſe foxes, theſe lytle foxꝭ, that vndermyne the vyneyardes and the lytle eyes of the vynes. which wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, howe they ſhulde be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyd I haue declaryd, in my enarracyon in to the cantycles. Farthermore wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I was about, an anſwere, in to the ſayde paradoxes, or concluſyons, the derely belouyd, and trewe teachyd bretheren of god <hi>VVLSGANGVS FABRI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CIVS</hi> Capito, and <hi>MARTINE BVCER,</hi> two of the byſhopes of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentyne, preuentyd me. And for that
<pb facs="tcp:9830:8"/>
cauſe I dyd leaue of my purpoſe and toke on hande, the reiteracyon or ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng forthe the comentaryes (whiche I had begonne) in to certayne of the prophetes, with many other thynges. for I knowe them to furnyſhe that mater, more dylygently then ſhal nede that any man ſhulde adde any thynge to theyr wrytingꝭ. I wolde but alonly moniſhe you, to beware, and take hede of ſuche wolues, goyng in ſhepes clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng, that they do nat in euery place vyolently rapte, ſlee, and dyſtroye. I haue alſo made anſwere, to the epyſtle that he dyd wryte to you in the begyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of his boke. deferrynge to wryte to you matters, of greater grauytye, vnto a tyme more conuenient, as well as if I had made anſwere to the ſayde paradoxes, or concluſyones. Nor you ſhall nat merueyle that I ſayde, there be many byſhopes of one cytye, for ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rely euery cytie, hath ſo many byſhop<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes, as it hathe true euangelyſtes or preachers, for euery preacher, of the truthe, I ſay of the truthe, that dothe nat preachelyes, decrees, inuencions, dreames, lawes, and cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelles, of men,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:8"/>
but the moſte pure and ſymple worde of god, is a true byſhope, although he be nat callyd ſo of many the churche of god, hathe no other byſhopes, but theſe. therfore there as is no pure mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the worde of god, is no byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, and without doute, we haue ben very longe and manye yeres without byſhopes, in the moſte fearfull iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of god, for they that haue be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd byſhopes, to this day, be nothyng leſſe than byſhopes, excepte they wyll be callyd wycked, or purſe byſhopes, or byſhopes of the kyngdome of anti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chriſte. Verely a byſhope is callyd by interpretacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an ouerſear or watcher, and euery man is byſhope of the thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g that he moſte entendythe. But there is no man ſo blynde, but he perceuyth to what thyngꝭ theſe byſhopes of the kyngdome of perdycyon entende. Ye and they glory them ſelues, in lyenge wordes ſayeng. He that dothe a thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, by another / aperethe to do it by hym ſelfe. This rule / is execrable / and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd byfore the lorde, in thoſe thynges that pertaine to the office of a byſhop whoſe hyeſt pointe is miniſtery of the
<pb facs="tcp:9830:9"/>
alonly worde of god, for they may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mytte to other the miniſtery of ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, bycauſe they be pryncypally ſent to the miniſtery of the worde. As ſaynte Paule wryteth of hym ſelfe, in the fyrſte epyſtle to the Corinthianes the fyrſte chapitre, ſayeng Chriſt ſent nat me to baptyze but to preache the goſpell more ouer theſe buggyſhe byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes, ſubſtitute or haue none vnder the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is a pure euangelyſt, but hyre wretches, and moſte couytouſe mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantes of lukre, that ſeke nothynge leſſe then the glory of god, and helthe of ſoules. I ſhall brefly intreate vpon with your hyghnes, of thoſe thynges that I copiouſly wrytte vpon, to the moſte noble lorde <hi>IOHAN</hi> Cardinal (as they call it) of Lotherynge. what the Pope, with hys Cardynalles, Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chebyſhopes, Byſhopes, Abbottes, Chanones, &amp; all other benefiſed men, ſhall do, leſte they peryſhe, but may be ſauyd. For of truthe / all theyr hygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is of the dyuell. Let them beware therfore / that they be nat euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gly confoundyd / and peryſhe. For byſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes be alonly ꝓphetes of truthe / and
<pb facs="tcp:9830:9"/>
there ſhulde be ſo many byſhopes, as the multytude of people requyreth. Ye and to confeſſe the truthe, I can nat call your hyghnes, a byſhope excepte I ſhulde flatre, and do agaynſt my con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſcyence, whiche is to be auoydyd of the faythfull, euyn as the venyme of the ſerpent Aſpis. I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe you to be a prynce, I knowe nat you to be a byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe, bycauſe you preache nat the goſpell. But it is nat in euery man, to preache the goſpel, but of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is gyuen of the lorde, for they muſte be ſende to it, of him. And theſe be the true byſhopes, of the churche of god. Therfore dylygently endeuour, your ſelfe that tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e byſhopes, may be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſyd, within your lordſhyp. Byſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes may nat be lordes, but alonlye doctours, or teachers, and ſeruauntes of the people of god. It is iniury to a prynce, to be callyd byſhope, ye and vtterly the moſte greuous mockage, if the thynge ſpoken, be delygently exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynyd, wolde nat be thynke hym ſelfe deludyd, that were callyd by a name nothyng <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for him? whan any man is callyd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, what other thyng
<pb facs="tcp:9830:10"/>
is it than to ſay, beholde a preacher of the worde of god, contynually prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng the goſpell, hauyng knowledge of holy ſcripture, teachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the people, with the alonly &amp; pure worde of god, attrybutynge to god hys due honour and prayſe, herberous, or kepyng hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitalytie, geuyng example of him ſelfe to other to folowe the goſpell in ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng, moſte dylygent in redynge and expounding the ſcriptures, and yet he hathe none of all theſe. I wyll ſuffre euery man to call you a byſhop, which I wyll nat do my ſelfe leſte I be iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous to you. I well knowe that you be prynce of Lauſane, ye and I wolde that you ſhulde ſo playe the prynce, that you wolde dylygently laboure to haue many true byſhopes vnder you. For verely euery paryſhe ought to haue hys propre byſhope, the whiche ſhulde be choſen of the people, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyrmed by the cominaltie of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of euery place, and to do this thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g they haue no nede of letters, rynges, ſealles, toke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and ſuche other of this kynde very muche vſyd clene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the worde of god. So longe they
<pb facs="tcp:9830:10"/>
ſhulde be accountyd for byſhopes as they preache moſte purely the goſpell of the kyngdome of god. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che if they ſwarue one iote, and teache ſtraunge doctryne, they ought to be depoſyd, and put out, of them by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were electe and choſen, that is to ſay of the comynaltie of the churche afore namyd, and other more apte to be electe. But of thys matter I haue ſpoken more at the large in an other place. Therfore I wyll returne to our purpoſe of Tregarius. He dyd wryte to your hyghnes ſuppoſyng you to be Fabiane, where as you be Sebaſtiane as the letters beare wytnes, gyuen to me by your owne handes, wherin he goyth aboute, to ſuppreſe and treade vnder fote the eternall veritie of god, vnder the name (as he hathe wrytten) of Lutherane ſecte, and vnder colour of zele towarde the church, he rayleth the moſte lyce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiouſly in to the truthe, and that ſame churche, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ho is he (at the leaſte) that ꝑceiueth the thyngꝭ of god, that folowith Luther, or ſayeth I am of Luthers ſecte? Luther is a man, and therfore of hym ſelfe a lyer,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:11"/>
but if Luther, or any other ſpeake the veritie, and truthe of god, what is the cauſe that we do nat gyue place to the truthe, whiche the holy ghoſte dothe make open to vs, by Luther? For I praye you is it nat wrytten of ſuche men: you be nat they that ſpeake, but the ſpirite of your father that ſpekith in you? it is nothyng ſauery, nor plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſythe nat at all, that ſome men do ſay, and talke of the wyſdome of god, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is founde in Paules epiſtles. they call it Paules philophie. I do gyue place, and beleue the wrytynges of Paule, Petre, Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Eſaie, Hieremie, and other prophetes of god, nat for them, but for the ſpirite of god, which dyd ſpeake in them. Luther hathe nat teachyd me, nother hys wrytynges, thoſe thingꝭ the which I haue knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the gyfte of god, in holy ſcriptures Yet for all that I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe, me to knowe Luther, ye and nat a lytle to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytyd thorugh hys company. I know him to be the apoſtle, and aungell of god, that is to ſay ſent of hym. For it is inpoſſible that he ſhulde be ſent, but of him, to haue wrytten thoſe thynges
<pb facs="tcp:9830:11"/>
that he hathe wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is, the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures of truthe, and euyn as it is nat to be condempnyd that Paule hathe wrytten bycauſe he was a man, in lyke caſe, nother Luthers wrytynges are to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempnid bycauſe he is a man. For it is nat Luther, but god y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hathe wrytten and ſpoken in Luther. But thꝭ Tregarius, to obtayne the fauour of Antichriſte, vnder the name of Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, dothe openly ſpeake agaynſte Chriſte and his viritie. He dothe alſo vnder that name reſyſte the impollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyd ſcriptures of god, all the prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, and his louers, and callythe them defenders of ſectes, cauſing great ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mores, repletynge the worlde with all vnquietnes, Philiſtianes haui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vaine and folyſhe armoure, mockers / and de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyuers / &amp; of this maner dothe rayle agaynſte them with the moſte oppro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brious crimes. Forthermore he dothe reproue them of vehemente and wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked zele / and ſaithe that they haue for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gote the ſaieng of our ſauyour. Lerne of me for I am meke and humble in harte and agayne. bleſſe them that ſay euyll of you / and praye for them that
<pb facs="tcp:9830:12"/>
perſecute you. But nowe loke vpon the craftynes of this foxe, ꝑauenture he is afrayde / leaſte that he ſhulde be put out and exilyd of antychriſt / from the tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nycall prouincialſhype of his ſecte / &amp; for that cauſe / he ſo feruently defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyth his parte / ſettyng at nought the worde of the lorde. Nowe if he take this for a ſecte / to loue and teach the moſte pure worde of god (the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che we doubte nat of) we do couit, and halfe this holy / neceſſary, eternal, and inuincible ſecte / and byfore hym and ſuche lyke / we wyll be of this ſecte / &amp; cleaue to it muſt ſurely / orels without remedy we ſhulde peryſhe ꝑpetually. we be adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders of thys eternall / heuenly / and deuyne ſecte / &amp; it is neceſſary / that we be tumultuous or bryngers vp of rumoures for it / a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt the execrable / curſid / and abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynable ſecte of antichriſte. For the worde of the lorde dothe burſt vp car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal peaſe / &amp; dothe rayſe vp the ſworde very ofte in hym ſelfe / accordynge to the ſayi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the lorde, I dyd nat come to ſende peaſe / but a ſworde. Math .x. and it is wrytten Luke .2. that Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:9830:12"/>
is put in to the falle (of the vnfaythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) &amp; in to reſurrection (of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) and in to a ſygne that ſhalbe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyſted and ſpoken agaynſte (of thoſe vnfaythful) if we ſhulde teache world<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly thynges / beyng carnall and hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crytes / they wolde nat reſyſt and ryſe agaynſt vs as they do, but bycauſe we preache thingꝭ co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the worlde, the worlde hatyth vs / and callyth vs tumultuous / and ſedecyous felowes. Ye and byfore it Chriſte him ſelfe was a ſower of euell ſedes / a ſclaunderer with wordes / a ſedycyous felowe / an herityke, a deceiuer, a ſubuerter of the people / and an euyll doer. Forther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more all that lyue mekely in Chriſte Ieſu / and couyt ſo to do / ſuffre perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cucyon of it. 2. Timoth. 3. God dothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde vs alſo / of Tregarius / and ſuche other men of that ſecte / whiche no doubte pertayne to the abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble courte of that purple whore of Babylon / mother of all fornicatyon / in the eyghtenthe Chapitre of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelacions of ſaynt. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayeng. Go from her my people / and be nat part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of her ſynnes / and receyue nat
<pb facs="tcp:9830:13"/>
of her plages / for her dampnable ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes haue come to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and the lord hathe remembryd her iniquities / re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde her euyn as ſhe rewardyd you / and gyue her double according to her workes. and powre in double in the ſame cuppe / which ſhe filled vnto you &amp; aſmuche as ſhe glorified in her ſelfe / and lyued wantonly / ſo muche powre you in for her of punyſhement / and ſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rowe. This wycked whore i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyme paſt hathe fylled to vs her abhominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / in the golden cuppe / of the worde of god. For ſhe hathe confyrmyd her ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannyes / by placys of ſcripture / falſly vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyd / and vnder the moſt holy name of Chriſte / ſhe hathe outragyd / aboue that at man can ſpeake / euyn a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſte Chriſte him ſelfe. Verely god wyll that we giue doble to her in that cuppe .i. better thyngꝭ then that dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke whore that is to ſaye / that we do nat fyll to other nowe, after the trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuyd / the abhominable / and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ynki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g dunge of the wyſdome of the fleſhe / &amp; inuencyons of men. But muche more pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cyous thingꝭ / the whiche do a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e with the golden cuppe of the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e of
<pb facs="tcp:9830:13"/>
god that is to ſay, the ſpirite &amp; truthe of the lettre, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is openly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that theſe iugelers be antichriſtes, ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>matykes, heretykes, chyldren of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion, and men of ſyn. To whoſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes bycauſe we do obey / and gyue place, they name vs to be ſclanderers, repleting al the worlde ful of rumours and horyble crymes. But &amp; I myght moue thys queſtyon to them in what thynge do we erre? I pray you do nat they with an indurat harte reſyſt / and ſpeake agaynſt the truthe. Ye and that ſame truthe it ſelfe doth name his ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myes, in euery place / wolues / Foxes Beares / Lyones / Dogges / Leoper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des / wylde beaſtes / falſe prophettes / pſeudo apoſtles, roten ſedes, vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, hypocrites, foliſhe, cowerdes, nat hearing the voyce of theyr lorde god, a baren howſe, the churche malignant the ſynagoge of Satan, the generacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the lordes furye, apoſtaticall genty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, hauynge the fronte of the greate whore, the fruyte and generatyon of Vipers, the counſell of the wycked, Dragones, the kynde of the ſerpente Aſpis deafe and ſtopyng theyr eares,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:14"/>
the ennemyes of the lorde, a wycked couent the tabernacles of ſynnes, the ſede of Chaname, Egypte, &amp; Sodome euyl trees and vnfruitful, mokers, that ſay to men ſayeng wyll nat you to ſee / ſpeake pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t thynges to our eares take hede of our errours, let holy Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell ceaſe from our ſyght, the blacke tayles of ſmokye bronddes, ydolles, blynde ſtudientes, the generacyon of Cain wycked and adulterous, decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable workemen, felowes of theuys, effemynate, deſerte chyldren, falſe doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>toures whoſe god is theyr belye, and glorie in theyr confuſyon, the taſters of earthly thynges, theues of innocen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, and wydoes, and dothe name the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that reſyſte, and ſpeake agaynſte the doctryne of mekenes, with ſuche na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of this kynde which of vs, coulde euer attayne to ſuche a vehemence of ſpeakyng. that in confoundyng the re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prouable, we might obtayne one parte of the pythye rebukyng that is fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de agaynſte them in holy ſcrypture. And peraduenture Tregarius wyll repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hende the holy ghoſte, and ſay that he dothe fyl the worlde ful of hatred and
<pb facs="tcp:9830:14"/>
malyce / bycauſe that ſuche names / ſhulde be putte in holy ſcripture, or at the leaſte ſaye that theſe be contrarye to Chriſte, when he ſaythe. Lerne of me .&amp;c. And agayne ſaye well by them that ſaye euyll by you .&amp;c. the whiche (as we haue ſayde) he dyd aledge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt vs. But what is the cauſe, that he dyd nat take hede, alſo of the word that folowythe, you? of men that ſaye euyll by vs we muſte ſpeake well, but nat of them that ſpeake euyll, by the lorde Ieſus Chriſte, and his verytye. No nor yet we maye nat make lyes, to ſay well by any man. For (and a man myght be bolde with you) is this well ſayde, to ſaye that <hi>Magiſter noſter</hi> the noble doctour Tregarius, a good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uande of Chriſt, and dothe well in ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>preſſynge the churche and worde of god, for the ſynagoge of Antychriſte and lyes of men. Or is it lawfull for me to wryte, the reuerende father in god, Prouyncial of the Auguſtyne fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ers, by the hyer Germanye, is a good oratour, and can wryte very well, for the counſelles of the Pope, hys Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynalles, and Byſhopes, and with a
<pb facs="tcp:9830:15"/>
noble profe openly declarith, that the Synagoge of the Pope, is the trewe church of god? am nat I rather bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to ſpeake playnly after the worde of god, &amp; ſaye. thys foxe, thys wolfe, this falſſe prophete is aboute to turne the people, frome the ſermones of truthe, to the lyes of antychriſt, and couytith to bryng the prynce of Lauſane, &amp; the noble gentyles of Heluetia, from god and hys Chriſte, and wolde that they ſhulde alway perſeuer, and continewe in darkenes of errours in the whiche we haue be drownyd ſo longe ſeaſon, and hathe nat one iota of ſcripture to confyrme thoſe thynges that he adfyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mythe in hys lyeng, wherof he muſte nedes fal. For he can neuer withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de the myghty worde of the Lorde, the whiche he ſo ſore reclamyth agaynſt, of whom he ſhalbe confoundyd, trode<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> downe, and conſumyd. Ye and if there were, innumerable thouſandes of the prophettes of Baalle, with this Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garius, they ſhalbe dyſtroyed, and fall from the ſyde of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that loue, &amp; teach the pure worde. One Helias, one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete of the lorde, ſhall ouercome, and
<pb facs="tcp:9830:15"/>
dyſtroye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all although they wolde reſyſte with playne batayle, and crye &amp; howle in theyr de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes. but in caſe that he thynke hym ſelfe nat worthye thys name, as to be callyd a foxe, or a wolfe let hym do none of theſe aforeſayde. for we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtraynyd to it by the word of god. for all that be of this ſecte, are to be publyſhed, to the people of god / that they maye beware of them leſte they be deceyuyd. Thys blynde doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toure, callythe vs, Phylyſtianes wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryng vayne and folyſhe armoure. and of this maner this blaſphemer railith and wonderythe, I wolde to god, that he were nat a blaſphemar agaynſt the ſpirite of god, and wolde nat ſpeake wittingly agaynſt his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, with what armoure do we reſyſte theſe ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of Chriſte and hys worde? Is it nat the eternal ſcriptures of god? and this iugeler callythe them vayne and folyſhe. But what is the cauſe that he was nat preſent at this laſte conflycte or diſputation, at Argentine, where he myght haue be ſure to haue dyſputyd with the Byſhopes of the ſame Cytie we wyl gladly giue our ſelues to deth
<pb facs="tcp:9830:16"/>
if we be ouercome, and conuicte, where as if he were co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicte he ſhulde ſuſtein no dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger at al. but he wolde nat that the people ſhulde knowe hys lyes, the whiche had be dyſcloſyd in dede, if he had dyſputyd, ye or to ſpeake near the marke if he had be preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t at the ſayde conflicte or dyſputacyon. the ſymple people, haue the iudgement of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite aboue al ſuche proude bugges the whiche we call <hi>Magiſtrinoſtri,</hi> bycauſe they loue the worde of god, the which the other be about to ſuppreſſe &amp; tread downe. For is it nat wrytten? Thou haſt made me wyſe, ouer myne enemies thorowe thy co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dmentes, for it is to me euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. I do perceiue, aboue all that teache me, bycauſe thy teſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies be my ſtudye. I vnderſtande aboue olde men, bycauſe I haue ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyd, thy commaundmentes. the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drethe &amp; .xviij. Pſalme. Forthermore fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe ſage and wyſe men, god doth hyde his myſteries, the which he doth voucheſafe to reuele and open to the yonge lytle ones. they knowe and per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue thys lyterature, and attrybute very muche to it, therfore they do nat entre in to the lordes power, verely
<pb facs="tcp:9830:16"/>
theſe other, be admytted into the ſayd powers and feareful iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god. For verely there is none although he be lernyd, that is admytted to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teligence of the ſcriptures of god, but euyn he that dothe attrybute or gyue nothynge at all, to the ſcyence or wyt of man towarde the vnderſtandyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but al only to the ſpirite of truthe. Theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyl nat that the lytle flocke of Chriſte, ſhulde iudge of his voyce, and it perteyneth moſt chefely to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For be nat they the ſhepe of Chriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; he theyr ſhepeherde? but there is one voyce alone of this ſhepherde or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, which doth hyely pleaſe his ſhepe without any other. And they knowe &amp; heare his ſaide voyce. Iohan .x. It is alſo ſayde to them, proue you the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites, if they be of god or nat. whiche they do ꝓue, &amp; knowe by the ſcripturꝭ of god, the which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> only &amp; moſt ſure teſtimony to proue, if the voycꝭ of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teache be of god or nat. alſo Pſal. 18 &amp; .118. &amp; Eſa. 8. they he callyd teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies or witnes. let thꝭ Tregariꝰ, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> all his ſecte, outrage as much as they wil and denye the worde of the lorde, that is to ſaye, that the companye of the
<pb facs="tcp:9830:17"/>
faythful to be apte iudgꝭ of the worde for w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out doubte he ſhal ſhortly ſlyde downe &amp; fale, bycauſe he goyth aboute it with ſtafe made of rede, of the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of Aegypte, of the dreames of men. If god be with vs who is agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſte vs? Let nat thys hartles knyght ouer boldely promyſe to him ſelfe the vyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie. I ſaye yet agayne he ſhall fale, &amp; be confoundyd. we be nat aboute this thorowe our ſelues, but thorowe the ſtone, that is, our faythe by Chriſt, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyteth to ſubuerte this lyeng and wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes. He hath his hedde, antichriſt to whom he dothe attrybute and gyue more then to Chriſte, and to whom he dothe cleaue with all his harte, the ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie and truthe of Chriſte ſetaparte. wherfore we of neceſſitie muſte nedes hate him accordyng to the ſayenge of Dauyd Pſalme. 118. I haue hatyd the wycked, and Pſalme. 138. Dyd nat I hate lorde them that hatyd the, &amp; was mouyd ouer thy enemyes? I dyd hate them with a parfecte hatred, and they were made enemyes to me. wherfore nowe in the meane ſeaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let him cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te vs for mockers, bycauſe we be apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta
<pb facs="tcp:9830:17"/>
from Antychryſt, &amp; curſſe him leſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we ſhulde be apoſtata from chryſt, and let hym opprobryoully ſpeake agaynſt vs what he wyl, for we glorye for them al byfore the lorde, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon is at hande, bycauſe that baren tre is not abaſſhed, to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayers of truth, for mockers, for no other thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but bycauſe they ſpeake the truth / as who ſaye / the truthe it ſelfe were a mockage. Thys wyked man wyll not be ouercome of the truth, of the which we glorye in the lorde to be conuycte, for we our ſelues in tymes paſte dyd walke i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpirite of errour, but nowe the veryte of god hathe ouercome vs, by the which god hath delyueryd vs, ye and dayly doth delyuer vs, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the moſt greuous darckenes of ignorance and erroures, whome we do inſtantly pray, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl make perfyte the thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche he hath begonne in vs, we wyl not be conuycte of the decrees of men, by whom he is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uycte, and moſt ſhamfully ſtraungelyd, as I very well knowe, ſo that in the thynges of god, he maye be confutyd, of innumerable chyldren, and huſbande men, for it is
<pb facs="tcp:9830:18"/>
to wyt, that the moſt vyctorous word of god, which they loue, is able to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueyle agaynſte a hundreth thouſande ſuche as Lregaryus is, if our armour be nat inuyctoryous (as he denyethe them to be) lette hym condeſcende or come forth, and proue howe inuycto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous they be, but he doth warre i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes, and charyotes, that is to ſay with the ſotletyes of men, verelye we warre in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name, and worde of our lorde god in the whiche we deſpyſe, hym and all that warre agaynſte vs, he dothe alſo ſay that the Churche, is not ſo deſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, namely in thys golden tyme, that ſhe ſhulde not haue her warryours, truely thꝭ myght be a ſainge of blynde Byarde oh howe nobly doth he know what the churche is, and who be her warryours, he ſuppoſethe the church to be that whiche countethe the wyſe men of the worlde to be her ſodyours, as who ſhulde ſay it were not wrytte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. I wyl deſtroy the wyſdome of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyſe and wyl caſt away the vnderſtandinge of the prudent, where is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyſe, where is the ſcrybe, where is the ſearcher of thys worlde, hathe not god made the
<pb facs="tcp:9830:18"/>
wyſdome of thys worlde folyſhenes. 1. Corinthy. 1. theſe be not the ſoudy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of the churche of god, but the ſymple, pure, meke, that with all theyr hartꝭ cleaue to the worde of god, moſt hyeſt, of ſuche, that be of thys kynde, the frunte of the greate warre of our churche which is peaſyble is ordyned the whiche is called by the Hebrewe terme Schulamitis, and not Sunami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis as be ſuppoſethe, for the Hebrewe bokes haue it wrytten of thys maner in the ſyxt Chapiter of the Cantikles <hi>Reuertere, Reuertere Schulamis.</hi> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which wordes in englyſhe be, returne, retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, or turne agayne my peaſyble chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and in the .7. chapiter. what ſhall ye fynde in my peaſyble churche, but companyes of warryours, ſpoken by thys terme, Schulamis, let hym haue hys churche, the whiche he callethe Sunamis, that is to ſay the ſynagoge of Antychryſte, myſerable, captyuate, ſtony, &amp; indurate, &amp; we wel haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ures the whiche we cal Schulamis, that is to ſaye, the churche of god, the ſpouſe of true Scholomon which is by inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prytacyon of Chryſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> peſable kynge
<pb facs="tcp:9830:19"/>
all whoſe ſouayours, ſtronge, ye moſt ſtrongeſt, be alwaye gyrded with the moſt perſynge ſworde of the worde of god, for nyghtlye dreades Lantik. 3. &amp; theſe ſouayours be made moſte ware and wyſe to the battelles into the con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iuringe of Antychryſt, whom god him ſelfe hathe made truely wyſe Ioh. 6. of whom the reprouable Aegipte So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, &amp; Babylon, be not able to ſuffer the leaſte ſcyrmyge, or lettynge loſe, nor neuer coulde. Thys Trygaryus, dothe ſaye, that we threaten greate thynges, but to whom, or do we threte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſelues, do not we rather open, and declare the thretenynges of the dread<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful power of god, the which we be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfyed of, ſhall fall moſt greuous into the kyngedome of the ſonne of perdy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon. he dothe alſo ſaye that in bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge vp rumoures, and ſclanders, we ſo perpetually be of one mynd, that no man doutethe of it, but we haue al one ſpirite, I make anſwere, that when we cal them wolues, beaſtes, antychriſtes we do not ſcla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſhewe forth what the ſpirite doth iudge of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by the teſtymonye of ſcryptures but it is
<pb facs="tcp:9830:19"/>
not alonly, in this one thinge; that we be al of one mynde, for we do dyſſente almoſt in nothyng, that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſpirite of god doth teach vs in the ſayd word he dyd propheſy as Cayphas dyd, ye euen agaynſte his wyl, nat dylygently markyng y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we hade al one ſpirite al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he wolde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his ſainge ſhuldbe otherwayes vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded. But nether be nor yet al his ſinagoge, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any thing be of one mynde, ſauynge in thys that they haue all coniured agaynſte god, Chryſt, and his verite, for what do we ſe in them perpetual ſtryfe, of Thomy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, Scotyſtes, Occaniſtes, of Nomy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nalles, Realles, Summeles, and ſuche other of thys kynde, ſtryuynge euen contrarye one to an other, whereby is wel knowen that they haue nothynge comen with the doctryne of chryſt, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whiche is the doctryne of mekenes, &amp; vnyte, &amp; they be alſo ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge from hys ſpirite, he doth furthermore ſaye that we with a vayne gloſe of wordes, do wraſt and wrythe the holy ſcryptures into our owne ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, wher as we do ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dewe our ſence by all meanes into the ſeruyce of the ſcrypture of god, and
<pb facs="tcp:9830:20"/>
glory to be ouer come<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the truth as any man may openly perceyue, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhal loke vpon our comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taryes, and alſo we do affyrme nothynge, that is not proued by the open teſtymonye of the ſcripture, what is the cauſe therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he dothe counte our expoſycyons for vayne, but that he is aboute with hys craftines to mocke &amp; haue in deryſion all the ſcryptures of god, wo be to the thou blynde iogeler, for thy iudgment is at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> arte not affrayed to count the teſtymonyes of god moſt hyeſt, for vayne and folyſhnes, peraue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture thou doeſte thynke the ſpirite of god to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared to thy doble crafty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, ye warſſe then a foxe, but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhalt ſhortlye be deſtroyed with the power of the ſame ſpirite, we wyll not cleaue to the counſel or phantyſe of any man excepte it haue the teſtymonye of the ſcryptures of god, in what thynge do we erre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or what haue we reprouyd at any tyme, that dothe agre with the ſcryptures of god, or what other thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges ſhulde we receyue, we do receyue the wryttinges of men, that agre with the ſayde ſcryptures, not for the men,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:20"/>
but for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> truth ſake, the word of truth ought to iudge, who ſhulde haue wryt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten ryghtfully / if they deny, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue the truth, let them improue our proba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyons, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god. Tregaryus wyll do it, he makethe argumente <hi>Pro</hi> and <hi>Contra, Primo, ſecundo, et tertio. &amp;c.</hi> we wyl heare this ſainge, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth it, to whoſe leaſt iote of ſpeaking ryghtly taken, we gyue place, but we openly accurſe the ſotletyes of Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garyus and hys ſecte, not bycauſe we be ignorant i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for we haue labored our ſelues in ſuch ſopheſtycal knottꝭ, but bycauſe it is wyked, and agaynſte the worde of god, to entreate apo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſcryptures of faythe, with ſuche con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencyous argumentes, nor we do not denye (as he dothe impute to vs) that the worde of god may not be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but we wolde not that this expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſycyon, ſhuldbe of the proper ſence of any man, althoughe he be learned, and holy, but of the ſence of Chryſt, which is than ſo, when we expounde ſcryptu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res. by ſcryptures, for as I haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in many bokes, it is impoſſyble, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any man ſhuld ryghtuouſly expounde
<pb facs="tcp:9830:21"/>
ſcryptures of hꝭ owne ſence or brayne And yet beſydes thꝭ Tregaryus hath added to, a blaſphemye agaynſte the lorde, that he ſuppoſythe there to be many goddes, that can be no maner wayes erre, the whiche doth perteyne alonly to god hym ſelfe the hyeſt, and greateſt, beſydes whom ther is no mo goddes, for who, but he is immutable, ſo that he can not erre, for all ſayntes haue ſynne .i. concupiſcence, as longe as they lyue and ſay as is wrytten, in the fyrſte canonycall epiſtle of Iohan the fyrſt Chapitre, yf we ſhulde ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue no ſyn in vs, we deceaue our ſelues and truthe is not in vs, but for all that they do not worke iniquite or wekydnes for ſyn dothe not reygne in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as is playnly declared Ro. 5. &amp;. 6. he is afrayde alſo leſt that he be iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous to the electe, &amp; in the meaneſe ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blaſphemyes the lorde, god hathe no nede of our lyes, no nor yet hꝭ ſayntes verely when god hath mercy of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, or the iniuſte, and maketh of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayntes theyr vnrytouſnes doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende, and laude y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rytouſnes of god Ro. 3. for verely from thenſforthe hys
<pb facs="tcp:9830:21"/>
iuſtyce apperythe more gloryous, and he is manyfeſtly declaryd to be iuſte, &amp; true, in hꝭ ſermones when he is cruell ouer the wekyd and the rebellyon not obſeruyng his promyſes is iudged, he dothe fayne hym ſelfe to wryte for the church of god, and yet dothe nothyng els: but aledge the decrees of men / for that thinge that this crafty falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete doth of the councelles, he doth it ſo that he is about to ſubuert al the pryncyples of fayth, I do confeſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſpeaketh many thinges true, chefly in the begynnynge, but at the laſte he doublethe his voyce of the churche, &amp; her councelles, wherby he maye more lyghtly &amp; ſurely powre out his poyſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but as I ſayde in the begynnynge he is anſweryd enoughe at al to his que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyons of them afore named, It dothe greaue me ſore / moſte noble prynce, to make anſwere to the wekydnes of thꝭ deceyuer, I wold but alonly gyue you warnynge, that you with al dilygence ſhulde flee, and auoyde, the poyſon of hym, and ſuche other, for you muſt do ſo of neceſſyte, if you wyl play y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true prince / or els it is impoſſible that you
<pb facs="tcp:9830:22"/>
ſhulde be ſauyd / nowe perceyue / I do thys with a greate hope / remembryng our olde amytye / the whiche in tymes paſſed / you dyd vouchſafe apon me / &amp; of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> noble mynde of your good lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppe / I wyl not go aboute to oynte your hede with oyle of a ſynner / the burden is great that oppreſſythe you, take hede therfore leſt you peryſhe vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der it / take hede alſo, that you haue vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der you / true chryſten people / and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chryſte may regyne in them / for then you ſhall cheflye play the true prince / when you chefly gyue delygence / that Chryſt maye be a prynce in your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes / take hede alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſt pure worde of god may be preached to you, banyſhe from your landes / al falſe pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes / wolues, &amp; ſuche maner of mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chande me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / &amp; I wolde that you ſhulde perfytlye knowe / that if youre people peryſhe your ſoule ſhalbe for theyres, ye if it be thorowe your cauſe, &amp; if ther peryſhe but one / pryncypally beware of al hoded men / for al they / excepte a fewe / haue coniured agaynſt god / and hꝭ chryſt / but aboue al other take hede of theſe, for they are to be flede of you
<pb facs="tcp:9830:22"/>
that glory them ſelues wykedly / with the tytle of obſeruantes / execrable to all Chryſtyanes / for theyr ypocryſye, hathe lede very many / ye almoſt innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable to death / I pray god y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hyeſt and beſt / that they maye ſhortly be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſyd / the courtes of al princes / &amp; by lytle, and lytle, it is hyely neceſſary y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you extyncte / &amp; put downe / the tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of the kyngdome of Antychryſt .i. theſe dyſceytfulnes of perdons ydola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>try of ſayntes that ſlepe / the offycyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les courtes / curſyd coſtomes / by no meanes to be permytted of Chryſtya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, the outragiouſnes of ſectes, with al ſuch other, &amp; then conceaue in your mynde, that you wyl haue holy ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures in your ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, &amp; ſtody vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nyght, &amp; day, the holy goſt wyl teache, and enforme you / by what meanes all thyngꝭ ſhalbe wel orderyd withi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your kyngdome, for &amp; yf you deny the word of god to the people, they ought not to obeye you, for they be the ſhepe of Chriſt they wyl be fedde with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meate of his holy worde, therfore al the peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of the faythful, maye ſaye to theyr princes / &amp; rulers, ye they be bounde to
<pb facs="tcp:9830:23"/>
make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregatyons for it, and ſay / we wyl heare the worde of our lorde god, we wyll not heare the decrees &amp; lawes of the pope / we wyl not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ecreralles of theſe gloſing ſophyſters, the which yf prynces / or rulers wyll denye them when they wylbe taken for faythful, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde people may depryue them theyr kyngdomes / &amp; lordſhypes / the people be ſubiecte / in al thinges, to princes, &amp; rulers / ſauynge thoſe thinges / that be againſt the worde of god / or that they ſhulde not haue the worde of god prea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ched / let your hyghnes gyue place to the truthe / and god ſhal encreaſe you in althynges / &amp; eſtablyſhe your kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. I was aduertyſed of late, that bycauſe a certeyne minyſter (as we cal it) a preſt, deſpyſynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> decre of anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryſt, prefarryng the precepte of god is maryed to a wyfe / for the which, he is taken priſoner of a certeyne tyrante thorowe your conſente, &amp; they do ſaye that he doth perſecute him to deathe / take hede, that you conſent not to any man, for your ſoule ſhuldbe for his, he hathe done a thynge neceſſary, which god hathe commaunded to al that can
<pb facs="tcp:9830:23"/>
not abſteyne, as I haue copyouſlye opened, in my boke of matrymony and euede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly proued it. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Kynge of Fraunce, the whiche I dyd put forth becauſe of my owne mariage for I am maryed, altho the ſynagoge of the ſon of perdicyon was madde at it, for we muſt rather obeye god then man, god hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded matrimony to euery man, that can not abſtayne, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope prohibyteth, and maketh ypocry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, to whom ſhuld we gyue place, not to god, the lorde dyd make no diſtync<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon betwyxte the layealtye, and the clargye the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundement is general perteyning to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of euery ſtate ye and if your highnes wyl beleue the truthe, take a wyfe, and by your exma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple you ſhal deſtroy this curſed decre of antychryſte, for when he dyd com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde to the Clargy, chaſtyte of ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge contrarye to the worde of god, he dyd multyply al maner of lecherye, and to ſpeke the truthe thys reproua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble order is ſpronge of no other thing but of dyſceytfull ſpirites, &amp; doctryne of deuylles, as you maye playnly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt of Tim, 4. the ſame iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gement
<pb facs="tcp:9830:24"/>
is of the prohybyting of meat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſame place very copyouſly I hade no ſpace nor tyme to wryt many thinges to you therfore I haue brefly made anſwere to that wyked Trega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryus wherin I haue putte moch good councel, bycauſe this deceyuer goeth about falſly to inſtructe you, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoryte of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>celles of the church of the which matter we hade comuny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catyon very oft in your palace, I ſhal alſo adde to .385. Paradoxes or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſyons / concludynge another thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge then Tregaryus hathe teached, I do alſo make redy my ſelfe, to anſwere to them al, where ſo euer it ſhalbe, eyther in Germanye or in Fraunce, or where ſo euer they wyl, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they wyll heare me, &amp; not go about to put me to deathe vn harde, I wyl dyſpute the matter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly if the counſel be holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and wyl no other iudges, but the moſt pure worde of god, and all that iudge ſyncerely after it, bycauſe it is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe lawefull, in caſe they ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me with the worde of god, and proue that I dyſſent from the truthe, in thoſe thynges that I ſhall affyrme
<pb facs="tcp:9830:24"/>
by the ſame worde, let them order me as they thynke it beſte, and yf they be conuycte, I wyl not that they ſhulde be in danger of the leaſt heare of theyr hede, but alonly let glory be gyuen to the truthe, wherfore I beſeche youre Lordeſhyppe to accepte thys trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſe of Paradoxes, or concluſyons, compendyouſlye concludynge almoſt all what ſoo euer dothe perteyne to Chryſtyanytye / and doo not dyſday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne my dewetye towarde your hyghe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / and perauenture God, the great<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teſte / and moſte hye, wyl graunte that I may ſhortlye put forthe vnder your name ſome thinge more exelent, peace and grace, of oure Lorde Ieſus Chryſte, and ioye of the holye goſt be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your noble lordſhip and with al youre peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. So be it. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:9830:25"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Christ on the cross</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:9830:25"/>
               <head>The fyrſte Chapitre. ¶ The cauſe of the greate blyndnes of the worlde, whiche hathe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued ſo longe tyme, by what meanes the verytye of ſcriptures of god hathe be hydde and ſuppreſſyd. Capi. i. The Paradoxes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>F Chriſt and his apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the ſame veryte &amp; truthe, was diligently preached, whiche nowe is opened agayne with his gyfte and ſpirite.</p>
               <p>They dyd preache the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> moſte pure worde of god, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerenes, that it was reuelyd &amp; ſhew yd of god: nat admyxted with proude phyloſophy, chyding ſophymes, drea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes, decrees, &amp; tradycyons, of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. and to do the ſame we our ſelues be a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boute, and couit with all our hertes.</p>
               <p>¶ For it is vnpoſſible, that any man <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> ſhulde perceiue the ſcriptures of god by carnal. wyſdome, as. S. Paule do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the ſay in his fyrſt epyſtle to the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians the .2. chapitre. ſayeng god hathe made them open by his ſpirite
<pb facs="tcp:9830:26"/>
for the ſpirite ſercheth althynges, ye the botome of godes ſecretes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> ¶ Verely the alonly ſpirite of god is the moſte lawfull interpreter of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures, and moſt ſurely dothe iudge of the ſecretes of god .i. Corinthians, 2. the thyngꝭ of god, no man knoweth, but the ſpirite of god. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> ¶ who ſo euer dothe preache and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde the ſcriptures, nat of this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite powres forth his dreames &amp; lyes for he is then carnall, nat perceiuyng thoſe thyngꝭ that be of the ſpirite of god, for they ſeme but folyſhenes to him. wherfore he can nat ꝑceiue that (as I haue ſayde) they be taken in ſpirite. 1. Corin. 2. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> God hathe gyuen to vs, the moſte ſureſt teſtimonie of his ſpirite, that is to ſay, his ſcriptures, by whom is wel knowen who dothe iudge rytiouſly or no. ſo ſcripture is called a witnes or teſtimonie. Eſaie. 8. &amp; the Pſalme. 18. and very ofte in the .118. Pſalme. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Euery expoſicion of any place of ſcripture, whiche dothe dyſſent, from no other place of the ſame ſcripture, is of the ſpirite of god, but if it do diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:9830:26"/>
in one iote, it is nat of the holy ghoſte, but commeth of the lyeng and folyſhe ſenſe of men, for euery man of hym ſelfe is a lyer. Pſalmus. 115.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Hat longe after the apoſtles dayes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> Doctours began to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, the moſt ſpirituall ſcriptures of god (agaynſte theyr propre nature, and ordre of god whiche had openid the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) after the wyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the fleſſhe, &amp; moſte vayne phy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>loſophy, admyxtinge them dayly with theyr reꝓuable ſoteltyes &amp; ſophymes.</p>
               <p>☞ By what meanes it came to paſſe, that they were depriued the equal iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gement of god, and true intellygence of ſcriptures, and blyndyd euery day more then other, ſo that by the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſophymes and carnall inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons the lyght of euerlaſtyng very<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye and truethe was vtterly hydde.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> wherof the moſte pure textes of ſcripture were forgotten, and inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures, feynours, and dreamars were receyuyd, as chydyng / Sopheſters / Scotyſtes / Thomyſtes / Occanyſtes Summyſtes / and ſuche other. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>☞ After that mannes wyſdome and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> proude phyloſophy was admytted, to
<pb facs="tcp:9830:27"/>
the expoſycyon of ſcriptures of god, whiche is inpoſſyble to it, for it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertyth the germane and true ſenſe of it, and we fall in to the moſte rude and ieoperdouſe confuſyon of blyndenes ygnorance and erroures that almoſte there ſhuldbe none that walkyth nat in lyenge. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Alſo nat longe after the apoſtles tyme, vnto theſe happy dayes, hathe be the very worldes of blyndnes and darkenes, but nowe the nyght &amp; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes be gone, and the amyable daye of verytie and truthe is at hande.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="11"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> It is hereſye to ſay, that to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uicte heretykes, we hadde nede of ſophiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal ſoteltyes or mannes phyloſophy. for veryly god is neuer knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nor they by hym, bycauſe no man may ſtryue, for god and hys veryte, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is contrary to God. Forther more the wyſdome of this worlde, is dyſtroyed, ouercome, and reproued, with the alonly and moſte pure worde of the croſſe. 1. Cor. 2. and the chapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre folowyng, Paule dothe ſaye that he dyd nat come to the Corynthyans in eloque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of ſpeakyng, or wyſdome,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:9830:27"/>
but that he might open and ſhewe the teſtymonye, of Chriſt Ieſu, and many thynges of thys matter in the ſame place. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>☞ They that beleue by eloquence, ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="12"/> phymes, philoſophy, and ſuche other wordes of mannes wyſdome, to tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che Chriſte, wyl that our faythe be in wyſdome of men whiche is inpoſſyble at the leaſte of true faythe, whiche is nat but of the worde of the croſſe and open ſhewynge of the ſpirite &amp; power of god. 1. Corynthyans. 2. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> In all the ieoperdouſe tyme of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roure <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="13"/> and darkenes, we were heryty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, ſyſmatikes, from Chriſte and his verytie, and drowned in the moſt gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſe erroures whiche we coulde nat perceyue of our ſelues, for bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alonly iudgement of the fleſſhe (that dothe neuer condempne it ſelfe, but is alway aboute to ordayne it, ye aboue god) was then receiued, &amp; dyd pleaſe, and men dyd cleaue to it whiche god dothe hyghly abhorre. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The lyeng and reprouable ſenſe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="14"/> and iudgement of the fleſſhe, then rey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yng. after that, and contrary to god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:9830:28"/>
worde. was inuentyd the ſupercy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyous, and proude ſtate, of the pope, his cardynalles, and byſſhopes, and what ſoeuer dothe perteyne to the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtatate kyngdome, as be the monaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tycall ſectes, indulgences of yeres &amp; dayes from pena &amp; culpa. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. decrees, and rules of men, vſurpyng of rythes, fyrſte frutes, and oblacyons, inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours .i. ꝓtectoures of this heryticall iniquitie, promocyons of falſe deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, ſcoles of decrees, and ſuch other of thys kynde execreable feynynges of the dyuell, by the whiche vnto the tyme apoynted, that is, vnto the tyme that the iniquities of this kyngdome of the ſonne of perdicyon was endyd, the ſame kyngdome was eſtablyſſhed,</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="15"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The ſureſt and moſte euident ſygne that this greate blyndenes hathe ſo longe endured, is that inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cions, tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyons, and decrees of men, were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardid and ſetby, more than the moſte holy lawe of god, and bycauſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pure textes and ſenſe of the byble, were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte clene extyncte and putte our of memory, beſydes that in theyr expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, euery man dyd folowe the drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:9830:28"/>
and feynynges of hys harte, and nat theyr true and germane ſenſe, nat the marke of the euerlaſtynge ſpirite, and dyd glory with hys inuencyons, ſo that there was none that myght be acountyd any thynge worthe at all in myniſtery of the worde, but ſuch a ru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ler, of whom might be ſayde. Beholde here a goodly preacher a noble pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e, with his newe inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cions, in preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and wrytyng he is copyous, &amp; moues mery conceites in euery place, that is as muche to ſay, as deryſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kage of the holy miniſtery of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and to be brefe, the byſſhopes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and prophetes, of god, were nat ſerchyd for. But Antychriſtꝭ and theyr ſynagoges whiche with theyr inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cyons with one brethe, can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke men bothe to laughe and wepe, vomyte a hundreth allegaciones, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng and preachyng to the people, de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crees and lawes of men, cuſtomes and deades of many yeres, examples and dreames, of olde wyues, monſtrous ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es of the kyngedome of Antychriſte, ypocrytes, deceyuers, lyers, nat wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyng to orden the iuſtyce of god, but
<pb facs="tcp:9830:29"/>
the iuſtyce of the fleſſhe, and of theyr ſectes and of antychryſtes nat ſekyng the glorie of god, but theyr owne glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie (they dyd all ſtryue for the pope, and the minorites for theyr Francys, Bonauenture, Scote, and Occam. &amp;c agaynſt Dominike, Thomas, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priolus .&amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. and ſo of other) ſlobelyes, deuouri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp wydoes, &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>noce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tꝭ how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, ye all the ſubſtance of the worlde.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="16"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Another ſure and euident token that this blyndnes hathe ben, is diſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon neuer ceaſyng that hathe bene, amongeſt preachers, for what do we ſe in them but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tencyon / debate / and chydynge agaynſte the nature of the holy ghoſte, whiche is ſpirite of vnyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and peace, and of the ſermons of god, whiche neuer ſofferith nature of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary oſnes in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and aganſt the cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the churche of god, whiche lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ueth true peace / and is enemy of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencyon. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="17"/> ¶ The thyrde &amp; manyfeſt ſygne, is ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>homynable peace of the fleſhe, for the worde of god bryngethe the ſworde, &amp; ſeperates chyldren from theyr paren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes / and frendes from frendes, whoſe
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:9830:29"/>
louers muſte nedes ſufre perſecucyon for it is vnpoſſyble that the worde of the croſſe ſhulde be without a croſſe, &amp; that it ſhulde nat be ſpoken agaynſt for Chriſte &amp; thoſe that longe to him, be put in ſygne of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tradictyon. Luc. 2. bycauſe therfore that the doctryne, that hath contynued ſo longe, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Antechriſte, the pryde, and al the apoſtaſy of his kyngedome, hathe be obſerued ſo longe tyme in an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable peaſe ſo that frely this man of ſynne with the tyrannes of his kynge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, what ſo euer they wolde, ſcarſly any man withſtandynge, dyd ordayne chaunge and dyſtroy, contrary to the playne textes of ſcripture, by what meanes it is well knowen, this peryl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe blyndenes to haue reygnyd by ſuche contynuance. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The .iiij. and moſte euydent ſygne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="18"/> is, that lawes, lycencyous lyuyng, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uylyſhe pompe, moſte proude orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, crownes, burletes, hattes, myters, hypocryſy hauynge no lyke, deceyua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble chaſtitie, dyuerſite and ſuperſticyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſectes, ſettynge vp of ydolles, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelles, colleges, phaanes .i. of hye and
<pb facs="tcp:9830:30"/>
monſtrouſe places, lyeng bulles, ſteli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of tythes fyrſt frutes and offerynges, vſurping of kyngdomes and lordſhyp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes, ſacryfyce of maſſes, and all other atteynyng to the kyngdome of Ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, clene contrary to the immacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat worde of god. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="19"/> ☞It was predeſtynat, that the ſonne of perdycyon, the manne of ſynne, the pope and his kyngdome, whom the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle. 2. Theſſa. 2. dyd propheſye, to be reuelat: and byfore that he ſhulde be knowen to be hydde, &amp; that by tyme and tymes, that is to ſay longe tyme &amp; halfe tyme, for the laſte tyme where as he thought to reygne perpetually, is cutte of the halfe, when he falleth by lytle and lytle, as he is knowen by the worde of god, he had neuer reigned ſo longe if we had knowen whom he had ben, all that tyme therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he hathe reygned vntyl he was knowen by and by, where as he is reuelyd, by the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye of god in the tyme p<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fynyte of god that is in our bleſſyd tyme, he begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth to falle, and is peryſhed with the ſworde of the mouthe of the lorde, and dayly he is toſſed &amp; plucked, without handes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:9830:30"/>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>And for that cauſe, the lorde hath <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="20"/> opened with his worde, fyrſte that the pope and as many as do pertayne to his kyngdome, be the chyldren of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dycyon, for no doubte who ſo euer is nat apoſtata and alyenat frome that kingdome is apoſtata and alienat and a ſcyſmatyke fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſte, wherof they may be bothe callyd chyldren of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dycyon and deceyuynge other with theyr lyes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Secondly, he hathe ſhewed, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="21"/> they be men of ſynne, bycauſe al theyr affectyons and cogytacyons and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes be ſynne. Alſo with theyr tradycy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, and ſynnes, they haue encreaſyd ſynne, aboue al eſtymacyon, there was neuer man from the begynnyng of the worlde that hathe ſo bounde mennes conſcyence as the pope and his tyran<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, that is cardynales, and byſhopes with theyr reprouable counſelles.</p>
               <p>¶ Thyrdly god hathe made manyfeſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="22"/> to vs, that who ſo euer hathe the pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macye of the churche of Satane, and is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the pope, is aboue al other the ſonne of perdicion, the man of ſyn and antychriſte, whiche dothe exalte
<pb facs="tcp:9830:31"/>
hymſelfe aboue all that is called god or worſhypped (ſuppreſſing the lawes and true worſhyppe of god) ſo that he dothe ſitte in the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god as god, and is taken of the faythefull, whiche be the quycke temples of god, for the vycker, of the hye god.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="23"/> ☞ Nowe afterwarde that god hathe manifeſtly ſhewed to vs, that the papa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cye, that is the kyngedome of Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, is the kyngedome of ſynne to be abhorryd and damnable, it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary for all that do attayne to it to be alyenat from it, and to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te them for nothynge but as dregges, or caſtynge out of dyuelles, to attribute nothyng to them, to truſte in nothing that they do, as in decrees, excominycacyons, pardons, pryuyleges, bulles, with ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che other bagage. And the ſame of the pope, cardynalles, patriarkes, legates archebyſhopes, falſebyſhopes, chano<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, and monkes, and ſo of all other.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="24"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> we haue a ſure knowledge, ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in .iiij. thynges that the doctryne whiche nowe is reuelyd, to vs of the lorde is the very and mere truthe, fyrſt that the pure textes of the byble, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:9830:31"/>
deceyuable inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cions of men abiecte. be dylygently receyued, wryten, and preachyd. The ſeconde is, that al ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cere preachers although they be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally ſeperate, nor one of them hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryth nat another or rede his wrytingꝭ yet do they for the moſte parte agree, but in caſe they dyſſent for a tyme, in any thyng then the ſcriptures of god, delygently ſerchyd, they be appeſyd &amp; contentyd. The thyrde is, althoughe many do abuſe the lybertye of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pell, yet as many as do receyue thys doctryne, gently, and mekely, be meke, mercyfull, faythefull, reioyſyng in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite, pacyent, very gentyll, full of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rytie, procuri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the glorye of god with out any ſuperſtycyouſnes, or hypocry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye, copyouſe in frutes of trewe good workes. The fourthe is, that this doc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tryne, is neuer reſyſted, nor ſpoken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſte, but of the chyldren of perdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon, carnall men, antechriſtes, and men of ſynne, euyn as Symeon dyd prophiſy of Chriſte, in the .2. chapitre of Luke, ſayng, in that ſigne that ſhall be reſiſted and ſpoken agaynſt. &amp;c. yet for al that they do nat ſpecially name
<pb facs="tcp:9830:32"/>
innocentes, and true preachers it can neuer be but they ſhalbe reſyſted and ſpoken agaynſte, for it is wrytten, if they haue perſecuted me, they ſhal per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecute you. Iohn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .15. cha. &amp; agay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne: all that wyll mekely lyue in Chriſt Ieſu ſhal ſuffre ꝑſecucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> .2. Tymo. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="25"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The electe, that haue gone byfore vs, in the miſerable time of errour and derkenes, althoughe they dyd aberre from the hydde iudgement of god, yet for theyr electio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that is bycauſe they were choſen of god frome the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng they were acceptable to him, for though he dyd abhorre theyr ſynnes, he dyd immutably loue theyr ꝑſones. For he by the purenes of theyr faythe hathe taken all theyr ſynnes, &amp; hathe nat ymputed them, for pure faythe is imputed to iuſtyce. Roma. 4. &amp; in the 33. Pſalme. Bleſſyd be they whoſe ini<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quities be forgyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and whoſe ſynnes be coueryd, bleſſid is that man, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lorde hathe nat imputyd ſyn. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If theſe electe ſhulde lyue nowe, no doubte but they wolde gyue place to the truthe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="26"/> ¶ For all that the electe do oftymes
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:9830:32"/>
erre (yet do they all ſay as is wrytten the .118. Pſalme. I haue erryd as a ſhepe that hathe peryſhed) but for all that they were neuer brought into er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, for they do neuer conſent to it, leſt they peryſhe in it, they do alwaye ſo erre that they ſay. Lorde my herte is redy, my herte is redy, verely they be alway redy if they were teachyd, to forſake all erroures.</p>
               <p>☞who ſoeuer couyteth, to be partta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="27"/> of the truthe nowe openid agayne muſte nedes confeſſe, al to haue ben in errour. For iuggelers in ſpirite, and doctryne of dyuelles, haue preueyled in theſe worldes of darkenes, in the moſte horryble iudgement of god. For ſo god had predeſtynate afore the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynninge, that in them ſhulde be tyme &amp; power of darkenes of the kyndome of antychryſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> And although this was chefely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gonne,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="28"/> in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> tyme the pope couyted, &amp; yſurped the primacye of the worlde, &amp; byſhopes nat co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent with theyr calle, but wolde be prynces and rulers, yet in the apoſteles tyme, the myſterye of i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iquite was wrought, in falſe apoſtles
<pb facs="tcp:9830:33"/>
and falſe bretherne as you maye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue. 2. Theſſa. 2 and .1. Iohanis. 4. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="29"/> ☞ They that can nat take the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of euerlaſtynge truthe, but wyll peryſhe perpetually, let them beware that they condempne them nat. For who can condempne the thinges that he perceyueth nat, and be without ſyn let hym humiliat hym ſelfe before the lorde, and confeſſe hys ignorance, whiche if he do in verytie, with out doute, he ſhall optayne, hys deſyre, for the myſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teryes of god, be hydde frome them that loueth car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wyſdome, and truſte to it, and be openyd to the meke, and chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren. Math. xj. Lu. x.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the holy churche of god, and reprouable ſynagoge of Sathan of canonyſynge, and inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of ſayntes.</head>
               <head>☞ The ſeconde Chapitre. ☜</head>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:9830:33"/>
               <head>The ſeconde Chapitre.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He churche of God is <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="30"/> the vnyuerſytie of all ſayntes, and them that be predeſtinate, whiche haue ben from the begin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng of the worlde, and ſhall be to the ende.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Eccleſia</hi> is a greke worde callyd in la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <hi>Congregatio</hi> in englyſhe a congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gation company or churche.</p>
               <p>¶ They be ſayntes, that be tranſlatid <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="31"/> from prophane or worldly thynges, to godly, and ſpirituall thynges, &amp; made holy and conſecratyd to god. That thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g is callyd holy i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſcripture that is nat comune, but ſeperate to god, ſo thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gꝭ were callyd holy in tymes paſte that were offeryd, in the temple of god, and then they were ſanctyfyed whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they were offeryd, and ſo we pray let thy name be ſantyfyed. That is we pray, that thy name that is to ſay thy fame, may be knowen and beleued of al men alone to excell all other and may be countyd for ſuche a one, as in very dede it is. And that all men may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that there is no prophane or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men thynge in the, but that thou arte
<pb facs="tcp:9830:34"/>
alone, holy / good / iuſte / myghty / euer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>laſtyng / nat hauyng another god lyke to the in thy maieſty.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="32"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> what ſo euer is of faythe is a holye thynge and iuſte, and he that workes / and lyueth, ſo of faythe, is a ſaynte / &amp; ryghtwyſe, and what ſo euer is nat of fayth, is prophane, and ſynne. Roma. 14. and they that do ſuche thynges be vniuſte / worldly / and vnclnee.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="33"/> ¶ He dothe lyue / and worke / of fayth that dothe al thyng with a ſure truſte, of goddes goodnes. beleuyng in hym that he ſhall receyue grace / and that nat by his owne meryte / but by the me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryte of Chriſte and his hye goodnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="34"/> ¶ To lyue of faythe / and worke of it or in the name of the lorde, or to hys glorye / be taken all for one thynge in holy ſcrypture.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="35"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Faythe is in euery worde of god / whiche is fulfylled, by the meryte of Chriſte and veryte of him that promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it / and it truly is nat virtuall / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytuall / or abydynge (as Sopheſters put. But actuall / true / hole / ſyncere / ſanctifieth, quickeneth, &amp; iuſtifieth, the beleuer. Abacuc .2. a iuſte man lyueth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:9830:34"/>
of faythe. &amp; Roma. 5. we beynge iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied of faythe let vs haue peace. and againe. Ro. 3. &amp; Galt. 2. euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall nat be iuſtified of workꝭ but of fayth.</p>
               <p>¶ All true faythfull, be ſayntes / and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="36"/> therfore Paule wrytyng to the faythe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, callyth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes. Ephe. j. Col. j.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The churche of god is inuiſible and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="37"/> ſpirituall, as faythe is, verely no man excepte he haue it by reuelacyon, can ſurely defyne of other, if they be of it, although there be many ſygnes, as is if any man wyll be ruled, in al thyngꝭ, with the worde of god, and profeſſe Chriſte in his actes. For it is wryten the prayſe of him, in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon of his ſayntes. Pſalm. 149. I do nat ſay them that be of the churche of god to be inuiſible, but the churche is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led inuiſible, bycauſe it is nat knowen by vyſible and corporall thynges.</p>
               <p>¶ For when the worde of the lorde,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="38"/> is preachyd, moſte purely it is neuer voyde without frute, but worketh all thyng, to which it is ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de of the lorde Eſa. 55. wherfore wherſoeuer it is ſo preachyd it is certayne, that there be ſome that be of the churche of god, in
<pb facs="tcp:9830:35"/>
whom it bryngeth forthe frute, but we can nat ſpecyally ſhewe one of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="39"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>The pope, ye with al his kyngdome with hym can nat ſurely ſhewe one ele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cte, or ſaynte, therfore they can cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſe none or a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcrybe them in the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of fayntes, for alonly god knowith whiche be his. 2. Timoth. 2. and thoſe to whom his wyll is to reuelate.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="40"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>Electe haue no nede, nor wyll nat at all any other canonyſer, be ſydes hym that dothe adſcrybe them in the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge numbre of hys ſayntes, and boke of them that do lyue.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="41"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Therfore all ſayntes, do hyely ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre the canonyſyng, of the pope, by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe it is no other thyng, then a fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng of the dyuell a ſtronge huntyng, a multyplycatyon of ydolles, decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng of the worlde, a turnynge frome the alonly Chriſte our true and moſte ſuffycyent medyatour, beſyde whome god wyll none. For all though god is to be prayſed, in his ſayntꝭ. Pſal. 115. Yet they be not our aduocates, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ought nat to call vpon them?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="42"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For that man Ieſus Chriſte the me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyatour of god and me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne. 1. Timo. 2.
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:9830:35"/>
is our aduocate, and a mercyfulnes for our ſynnes. 1. Iohannis. 1.</p>
               <p>¶ The holy mother of god, and all <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="43"/> ſayntes do abhorre, aboue that at can be ſpoken, and hate vowes and pylgry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mages, to theyr ſepulchres, and buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge of chapelles, and ydolles, and ſuche other of this kynde. by cauſe by theſe, the people, be turned frome ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere truſte in god, and his Chriſt, of al meruels, and wonders, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>el of theſe as of all other lyke. I haue ſpoken of in the boke of the cauſes of the blynd<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. tracta. 5. capi. 12.</p>
               <p>¶The pope and other with hym, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="44"/> canonyſe, vſurpe that whiche is ꝓpre to the alonly god, that is to adſcrybe and numbre, his electe.</p>
               <p>¶ To adfyrme that the pope, or any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="45"/> other men may canonyſe, the electe of god, it is heryſye, bycauſe it dothe diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſent from holy ſcrypture.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Alonly the electe, whom god hathe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="46"/> adſcrybed in the eternitie, and numbre of his ſayntes, be of his churche. But vnto they beleue they abyde without the churche.</p>
               <p>¶ For any man to be of the churche <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="47"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:36"/>
of god kynde condycyon, age, nacyon coloure of clothyng or deynteouſnes or any other outwarde thynge nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g profyteth. As is playne. Galath. 3. Coloſſ. 3. but ſyncere faythfull, do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myt no outwarde thynge that dothe nat agre in all thynge with the worde of god.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="48"/> ☞wherof it foloweth, that it is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye to adfyrme that the pope, cardy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles, byſhopes, with all his kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, be of the churche of god, which is meke all pure and holy. Forther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more (as I haue ſayde) it is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uiſible .i. it maye nat be knowen ſurely, by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde thynges althoughe it haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the externe workes of faythe. for it dothe althyng of faythe, whether it eate / drynke or any other thyng. But that it dothe thys of faythe there is none but god, and he beynge worker that ſeeth.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="49"/> ¶They that be of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon / of the wycked / haue ofte workes ape<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryngly good / &amp; very ofte apere to the electe to be more holye for it / verely god knoweth that all theyr workes be euyll bycauſe they be nat of faythe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:9830:36"/>¶Therfore of faythe / and infidelyte / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="50"/> good workes and euyll iuſte / and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſte / do come.</p>
               <p>¶who ſo euer lyueth nat and worketh <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="51"/> of this forſayde faythe / is of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany / and ſynagoge that is ſpoken of Pſalmo. 23. I haue hatyd the churche malygnant / and. Apocalip. 2. I knowe theyr blaſphemyes that ſaye they be Iues / and be nat / but be the ſynagoge of ſatane. and agayne. capitulo. 3. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde I ſhall gyue of the ſynagoge of ſatane that ſay they be Iues &amp; be nat.</p>
               <p>¶ Of this kynde / is the hole churche <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="52"/> of the pope / it is ſo muche leſſe that it ſhulde be / of the ympollutyd churche of god.</p>
               <p>¶ All that be of the ſynagoge / of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="53"/> pope wyl be callyd eccleſiaſtycall / and there is no lye more open the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this. If thou do referre this name to the chur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che of god / in a reſpecte they may be alonly callyd eccleſiaſty call or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall to the churche of the deuyll.</p>
               <p>¶ Therfore bycauſe / the kyngedome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="54"/> of the pope / hathe nothyng comen / with the churche of god / as many as perteyne to hym / be the very chyldren
<pb facs="tcp:9830:37"/>
of his worlde / veryly all other / if they be noble men or marcha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, artificers / or huſbandemen / ſo that there be ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere faythe / in whiche they lyue / and worke / and dyſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t from the kyngdome of the pope / be eccleſiaſtycall / and of the churche of god / to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe ſciſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matikes haue done the moſt poyſened iniury and wronge bycauſe they haue callyd them ſeculer and carnal or tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral / and they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundyd with a hatefull pryde them ſelues to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="55"/> ¶ Verely who ſo euer is of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of god is eccleſiaſtycall and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall / and dothe all thynges of fayth / whiche be ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="56"/> ¶ The ſinagoge / of the pope is more aduerſary to Chriſte / then the turke / for the emperoure of trukes ſofferyth faythfull that be in his landes / to ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue after the pure worde of god / whom theſe blynde enemyes of mekenes / dothe nat ceaſe to reclame agaynſt in the myddes of theyr blyndnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="57"/> ¶ wherfore it were better for vs to ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue vnder the empyre of the turke / then the pope. truely it is lawfull for fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:9830:37"/>
to lyue vnder any prynce / ſo that Chriſt &amp; his worde be frely ſufferid, as it was lawful for the Iſralites to lyue vnder Nabugodonoſor, Cyro, Daryo, Aſſuero, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Romanes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Aſſerye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s .&amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> From this forſayde ſynagoge there <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="58"/> may none paſſe, to the churche of god excepte he fyrſte forſake the pope, and his decrees, for the pope, and Chriſt, be more contrary then fyre and water.</p>
               <p>☞He is the very greate and true an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techriſte,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="59"/> and all the tyrannes of hys kyngdome .i. cardinalles, and byſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; they that do nat dyſſent fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym be alſo antichriſtes.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Euen as it was neceſſarye to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="60"/> bleſſyd angelles, to theyr eternal hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the, to dyſſent from that fyrſte angell apoſtata, ſo to all that couit to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, it is neceſſary to be alyenat from the pope, and his ki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gdome orels they ſhall neuer truely knowe Chriſte and cleaue to his verytye, with full herte, wherfore they muſte nedes peryſhe at the laſte. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the comunyon of ſayntes of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comunicacion &amp; bulles of the ſon of perdycyon. Capi. 3.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:9830:38"/>
               <head>The thyrde Chapitre.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="61"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll that be of the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of god, haue theyr comunion to gyther of one faythe, one ſpirite, one grace, truthe, iuſtice peaſe, baptym, and of al gyftes of the ſpirite.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="62"/> ☞Alonly by faythe they that beleue, be partakers of all theſe. For all the workes of god be in faythe. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Bycauſe the kyngdome of the pope lyuys nat of faythe, it can haue none of theſe it is ſo muche leſſe, that it can gyue them to other. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> It is hereſye to afyrme, that by the curſyd indulgences of the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the pope the grace of god or remyſſyon of al ſines or of the thyrde or forthe or halfe parte or of one only ſynne is grauntyd. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="65"/> ☞And the grace of god, whiche is of faythe alonly be <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, al ſynnes be for gyuen, &amp; nat ymputyd. But if it be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, none is forgiuen, but al ymputid.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="66"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Therfore nat one or ſome parte of ſyn is remytted, but all to gether o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther remytted or holden. For that ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is bleſſyd alonly, whoſe iniquityes be
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:9830:38"/>
forgyuen and coueryd, and are nat ym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>putyd. Pſalm. 31. ſo that if one ſyn be retayned, yet dothe other remayne ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tred, and curſydnes. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Bulles, Iubylyes, and all pardons,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="67"/> of the kyngedome of the pope, be no other thynge, but dyſceytfulnes, dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelyſſhe iuglyng, ſure nettes, to drawe all the ſubſtance of the worlde, curſyd marchandyſe, fedynge of the enemyes of god, an abomynable inuencyon, tur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſyncere faythe of Chriſt alonly profytable to dyſtroye ſoules, and noryſhe ſatannes ſynagoge. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> who ſo euer, dothe truſte to theſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="68"/> falſe bulles, &amp; dothe nat perceyue that they be dyſtructyon, he is blynde and ſhall neuer obtayne the grace of god by them or remiſſyon of one ſyn, what ſo euer he dothe or gyuethe therfore.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Alonly god receyueth the electe of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="69"/> faythe, to the aforſayde glory and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munyon of ſayntes, frome the whiche he alone makyth infideles ſtraunge.</p>
               <p>☞ wherfore no man lyuyng, neyther <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="70"/> popes, nor theyr byſhopes, nor all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles, and men togyther, can depryue any man, the comunio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the faythfull
<pb facs="tcp:9830:39"/>
or lawefully denounce hym for ſuche one, excepte fyrſt it be ꝑfeytly knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, by teſtymonye of ſcrypture, that he be depryuyd it of the lorde. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="71"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Euery churche of the faythfull, and who ſo euer berythe rule, as kynges, prynces, and offycers, where as cauſe is, may ye they ought, do de<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ue theyr ſubiectes the outwarde company of the faythful, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is they ſhall nat dwell with them or otherwyſe kepe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="72"/> ☞The cauſe for the whiche many be depriued this outwarde comunyon, is by adultery, horehu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyng, thefte vſure, curſyng, couytouſenes, cruelnes, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kenes, to be reproche to the churche of god. 1. Corin. 5. and to be apoſtata from Chriſte is to ſpeke a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſte the doctryne of mekenes and nat to ſufre it. As is euydent the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde canonicall epyſtle of Iohan.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="73"/> ¶ No congregacyon, of the faythful, may lawfully other dreade or receyue the abhomynable coſtomes, interdite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes or decrees of the kyngedome of the pope, for truely they can hurte them that beleue no maner wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="74"/> ☞ In caſe any man, for thynges that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9830:39"/>
agre with the worde of god, or bicauſe he is rulyd by the worde, be excomuni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate, curſyd or enterdyted, of the pope or his, it is turned to him i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to the moſt precyouſe and amyable bleſſynge, for when they curſe god bleſſythe. Pſal. 108. and to thoſe that loue god all thinges be wroght in goodnes. Ro. 8.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>¶Of true goodworkes and the lawe, of grace, and the goſpell, and vertues of the faythfull. Capi. 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll though we be iuſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied alonly by fayth yet <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="75"/> workes be neceſſarye.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Faythe is neuer with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="76"/> out true goodworkes, for he hathe his effyca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cytie by loue. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Trewe good workes be, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="77"/> is of faythe, ye to eate, to drynke to ſlepe, ſo there be no exceſſe. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> what thynges that be nat prohibite <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="78"/> by goddꝭ worde, may be done in fayth other may nat. ☞ : <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> : ☜</p>
               <p>☞what ſo euer is nat of faithe is wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="79"/> though it apere outwardly good / iuſte, and holy. Roma. 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:40"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="80"/> ☞Faythfull to do well, haue no nede of decrees, and tradycyons, of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="81"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Theſe be doctryne, lawes and tra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dycyons, of men that do nat conſent, with the ſcriptures of god, or els they parteyne to them, for the doctryne of man is lyeng, bycauſe man is alyer. Pſalm. 115. trewely the worde of the lorde is verytye. Pſalme. 118.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="82"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The lawe of god is ſuffycyent, for faythfull whiche is the lawe of the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rite wrytten in theyr hertes. Eiſai. 51. and Hiere. 31. whoſe ſcriptures be the moſt ſuryſt wytnes of the lorde. Pſal. 18. &amp;. 118. and the ſpirite dothe wryte in them the goſpell of peaſe, and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtynge healthe, whiche is no other thynge but a ſurenes of the grace of god and remyſſyon of ſyn, by fayth in Chriſte, and his truthe, whiche whoſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>euer preachythe purely is an euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſt. For the goſpell is a gladde and good tydynges. ☞ : <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> : <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="83"/> ¶ For that ſame ſpirite dothe teache them all truthe. Iohan. 16. and is go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerner of them in euery thynge. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="84"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> It is hereſye to ſay, that ſcriptures of god, be ſuperfluous. for they be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:9830:40"/>
&amp; that hyely, that we maye be ſure if thoſe thyngꝭ that be in our her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes be of god or no, for by what reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as I haue ſayde) ſhulde we be more ſure, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſcriptures of god, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che be his teſtymonyes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>:<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>☞ And althoughe we had nede, of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="85"/> ſame ſcriptures, for witneſe of truthe, yet for all that, euery ſermon of the worde of god and all ſcripture is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profytable and in vayne, excepte it be wryten in our hertes, of the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, whiche ſcripture of the ſpirite is the quicke voyce of god. ☞ : <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> : ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> wherfore it is hereſye to affyrme <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="86"/> that there is any other quycke voyce of god neceſſary beſydes thys and to ſuppreſſe his meruelouſe teſtimonies. Pſalm. 118. as many falſe prophetes do nowe adayes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Therfore the teſtymonyes of god <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="87"/> muſte be preached, and it is neceſſarye to be conuerſant in them with all dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lygence, which who ſo euer dothe tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly is verely bleſſid. Pſalm. 1. and .118. but the fruyte of that preachyng and conuerſacyon, muſte be lokyd for of the holy ghoſte. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:41"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="88"/> ☞ The pryncypall vſe of thoſe ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tures of god, is that we maye ſerche in them the teſtymonyes of his godly wyll. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜: ☞</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="89"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Verely the frute of them is, that we beleuyng may be iuſtyfyed, that is, we may gette the grace of god and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſſyon of ſynnes. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="90"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The grace of god, is nat that qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyty that Sopheſters call <hi>Habitus,</hi> but the fauour and beneuolence of god, hauynge vs free when we beleue hym and he hathe his grace that is kynde to hym. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="91"/> ☞ Alonly by the merit of Chriſte, we beleuyng in him, and nothyng douti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of his wordes, we gette this grace. for then we do receyue hys plentifulnes. Iohan the fyrſte chapitre.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="92"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Faythful receiued in to the grace of god, by Chriſte, haue togither by hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that iuſtyce whiche hathe in it all par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fytnes. Of the whiche is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pſal. 71. Iuſtyce and aboundance of peaſe ſhal ſpryng in his dayes. And Pſalm. 84. mercy and veritie haue mette him peaſe &amp; iuſtyce haue kyſſed hym, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:9830:41"/>
alſo of this is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Eiſaie. 53. in his ſcience, he beyng iuſte ſhall iuſtify my ſeruantes very many. ☞<g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Bycauſe therfore that faythefull,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="63"/> haue all thynges in Chriſte, it is ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous, curious, and alſo dampna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to ſcarche ſo many partes kyndes and offyces, of vertues as falſe Deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes do, for they that intende ſuche thyng, be but curyouſe, for they put ſo many pertykeles, that it is vnpoſſyble to remembre all, as you may perceyue manyfeſtly i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>leles of Thomas.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Rede what god dothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="64"/> and be ofte couerſant in his ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and thou ſhalte be full of vertues, all thoughe thou neuer knowe ſoo many na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes partꝭ and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices as they putte.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>¶ Of the preſthode of the faythe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and trewe mynyſters of the churche that is byſhopes, and deaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. The fyfte Chapitre.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:9830:42"/>
               <head>The fyfte Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="95"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſthode of chriſt and mynyſters of hys churche, the preeſthode of Aaron &amp; miniſteryes of hys deacons be abro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gat and put downe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="96"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Chryſte alone is the bye byſhope, and preſte of the church Pſalmo. 109. Hebre. 5. and. 9. full of grace and truthe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="97"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> As many as beleue in hym be made pertakers of hys plentyfulnes. Io. 1. and of hys oyntment, that is of the holy gooſt. Pſalmo. 44. O god (the ſone) thy god, the father hath oynted the with oyle of gladnes (the ſpyryte makynge glade) aboue thy felowes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is other faythful whiche be pertakers of thy plentyfulnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="98"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> All faythful of both kyndes be con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſecrate into preſtes by hym, as Peter wryteth to all faythful. 1. Pet. 2. you are a choſen generacyon, a ryall preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode. Apocalip. 5. thou haſte made vs kynges and preſtes to our god, and we ſhal reygne apon the erthe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="99"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> I do not call them ſeny ours by the greke worde <hi>Preſbitri,</hi> but <hi>Saſerdotes,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:9830:42"/>
whiche we call preſtes for <hi>Preſbiter</hi> is a greke worde, and ſygnifythe a ſeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our or elder, and is proper to the hye mynyſters of the churche, as byſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, or preachers of the worde of god, <hi>Sacerdos,</hi> whiche we call a preſt is who ſo euer is ſacrated to god by faythe.</p>
               <p>¶ Euery true ſenyour .i. euery true <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="100"/> mynyſter of the worde is a preſte, but euery preeſte is not a ſenyour or my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The pope with all hys byſhoppes,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="101"/> and all the worlde together can not make one preſt of the churche of god, for it is alonely goddes offyce, which dothe ſanctyfye hys electe in faythe / and dothe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate them into preſtes for hym ſelfe.</p>
               <p>¶ Preſthode of the kyngdome of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="102"/> pope was inuented of men / without the teſtymonye of the worde of god / &amp; came forthe by the ſtrenthe, and eyde of the deuell.</p>
               <p>¶ Preſtes of that kyngdome can not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="103"/> be preſtes of the kyngdome of Chryſt except firſte they do forſake the preſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode of the pope .i. they ſhal not truſt or attrybute any thynge to him / altho
<pb facs="tcp:9830:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>
for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyme they admyt many thynges for the infyrmytye of other.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="104"/> ¶ In place of mynyſters of the lawe, as preſtes and leuites / there be alonly two kyndes of mynyſters vnder the goſpell / byſhoppes / and deacons.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="105"/> ¶ Euery ſyncere mynyſter of godes / worde / is called in ſcrypture by theſe names / fyrſte an ouerſeer. Ezechiel. 3. ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly / a prophet. 1. Cor. 14. therdly an euaungelyſte of the goſpell that he preacheth / Eiſaie. 41. I ſhall gyue Hyeruſalem an euaungeleſt. Ephe. 4. other truly euaungeliſtes, &amp; it is ſayd. 2. Tymo. 4. do the worke of an euaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelyſt and. Actes. 21. entrynge into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> houſe of Phylyp the euau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelyſt ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / Mathew / Marke / Luke / &amp; Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be not alonly euaungelyſtes / but all true preachers of the ſcryptures of god / fourthely eccleſyaſtycal .i. aprea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher <hi>Eccleſia.</hi> i. the church is a congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacyon therfore he that rulythe hyt with the worde, is called a preacher / fyftely a ſeniour or elder .i. Tymo. 5. ſenyours that gouerne wel be worthy double honour / and alſo / agaynſt the ſenyour, ſyxthely a byſhope that is an
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:9830:43"/>
ouerſeer .i. Tymoth. 3. a byſhope muſt be fautles / and to Tytum. 1. a byſhope muſt be without blame / and Act. 10. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy gooſt hath mayde you byſhopes ſeuenthely an apoſtle / for apoſtle is a meſſenger and ſente / and cometh of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> greke worde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſygny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyth to ſende that is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye for the mynyſters of goddes worde / to be hys apoſteles that is to be ſente of hym Rom. 10. howe ſhuld they preache except they be ſente / but ſome be greate apoſtles and ſome leſſe 2. cor. 11. Alſo that you may knowe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> office of a biſhope &amp; apoſtle to be both one / when Peter Actes. 1. ſayde that ſome man muſte be deſyred into thys mynyſterye and offyce of an apoſtle / from which Iudas was exyled, he dyd aledge this place of Dauyd and hys byſhoppryke another ſhal poſſeſſe.</p>
               <p>¶ You may gather therfore / becauſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="106"/> neyther the pope / nor byſhoppes / or tyrantes / of his kyngedome haue any of theſe afore ſayde / they be not of the churche of god ouerſeers / prophetes euaungelyſtes / preachers / ſenyoures / byſhoppes / or apoſteles / excepte you
<pb facs="tcp:9830:44"/>
ioyne thys terme falſe to euery one of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="107"/> ¶ Cetyes and townes, which haue no paſtore / ſymply preachynge the moſte pure worde of god / haue no byſhope / ſenyour / preacher / or euaungelyſte / of Ieſu Chryſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="108"/> ¶ In many cetyes / all that be of the reprouable ſynagoge of antychryſte / perceyuinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the immaculate worde of god ſettes openly forth theyr abho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mynacyon / they do ſo hate them / and dreade leſte any true mynyſter of the worde ſhuld be harde of the people / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> aſſone as any commeth / before he can open hys mouthe they go aboute to ſtope hym / whiche I haue proued my ſelfe very ofte / ſpecyally in the noble cetye of Wetens in the whiche god hath delyuered me ofte from the han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of antychryſtes ſekyng my ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="109"/> ¶ There was in that cety / that tyme a holy byſhope of god / nowe a bleſſed martyr &amp; witnes of Chriſt ſaynt Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> caſtellanc / whome for the teſtymonye of truthe the apoſtate kyngedome of the ſone of perdycyon vehemently ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge / when they coulde not hurt him
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9830:44"/>
in the cetye / they brought to paſſe / by treaſon / that he ſhuld go forthe of the cetye and he ſo banyſhed they toke hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pryſoner by &amp; by afore the .9. monthe whome Anthony abbot with a falſe procter / &amp; many falſe pharyſyes were aboute to brynge hym to that paſſe / y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he ſhulde denye Chryſte and hys ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte. But the holy champyon of god perſeuered immouable / and was neuer ouer come / the lorde confyrminge his breſte with hys ſpirite / then they mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr reprouable myndes / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laſt of all that is the .12. day of Ianuarye Anno .1525. at vuy a towne of lothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe the ſame Iohan reioyſynge and beynge glade in the lorde / not warned before of it / but led to execucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / when that he wolde not recante into the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure of antychryſte they made him a gloryous merter of Chryſt / with moſt cruel torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes of fyre, &amp; who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they dyd couet to extyncte / they crouned with a incomperable dyedeme of glorye / euen agaynſt theyr wylles ſo that if it were lawefull to call apon ſayntes he were to be named no leſſe then Peter or Paule &amp; other apoſteles / but there
<pb facs="tcp:9830:45"/>
is one aduocate and our mediator the lorde Ieſus Chryſte. I haue brought thys paradox that we maye gloryfye this ſaynt Iohan in the lorde and the lorde in hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / and alſo that hys burners and bochers / may ſe theyr fautes / and moſt greuous cryme / and may amende leſt they periſhe / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord Ieſus Chryſt make them of Saules / Paules / that is of the enemyes of Chryſte and hys truth / his frendes, and of perſecuters defenders and his preachers.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="110"/> ¶ There is nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be no true biſhope of the churche of Ieſu Chryſte / but a pure and euaungelycall preacher / for other proude blowen pompes bugges of the kyngedome of the pope be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge leſſe then byſhoppes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="111"/> In euery cety / towne / &amp; village there ought to be many byſhoppes .i. euaun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gelyſtes or preachers / after the quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyte of places &amp; multytude of people.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="112"/> ¶ Yf many peryſhes be ſo great / that one byſhope is not ſuffycient for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be deuyded / and to euery parte a byſhoppe aſſygned / theſe two con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions I haue expounded in my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſycyon
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:9830:45"/>
of the rule of the Mynory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. Capitulo. 15.</p>
               <p>¶ It is neceſſary for biſhoppes to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="113"/> ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and called of god / and that I haue proued in the ſame. 15. Chapi. of the ſame enarracyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the boke of callynge</p>
               <p>¶ It is the moſt greuous cryme / and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="114"/> by no menes to be ſufferyd / that many chyldren of perdicyon do depryue the people of god theyr ryght / and iuſte tytle, that is to choſe them a paſtor / for he ſhulde be choſen of them / that is ordeyned for them to rule with the worde.</p>
               <p>¶ Of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="115"/> he is to be taken for a true byſhop and meſſenger of god / whome ſo euer he dothe ſende / altho thys ſendynge be by lot of faythe openly done / as of Mathy. Actes. 1. as I haue declared in my ſayde boke of callynge.</p>
               <p>¶ The counſell of euery place ought <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="116"/> to gyue hede and watche if thoſe that be choſen into byſhopprykes be mete to the ſame miniſtery of euery peryſhe of the faythfull / whiche belonge che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fely to prynces.</p>
               <p>¶And yf there chaunce any to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecte <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="116"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:46"/>
vnprofytable, vnlernyd, or ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge from the worde, or that dothe offende the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon of god by horemon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge or any other cryme, or not wyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to admytte holye matrymonye, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge a vnchaſt wyfe, or childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tynge from mekenes. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. the electyon muſt be reuoked of them, and lette the electyon turne to the congregacyon that they may cal a byſhoppe to them myghtye in workes of mekenes, and the worde. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="118"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Yf the churche dyſſent in electyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a byſhoppe, or rulers and prynces, with the churche, nor they do not ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arche the counſell of the lorde of true byſhoppes, nor fynde one open place of ſcrypture what is neceſſary for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to do, then by example of the apoſtles faythful prayer had before, lette them caſt loottes, and what ſo euer chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſythe by lootte, they be bounde to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue for the ſure wyll of god, for it is written, loottes be put into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> boſome and tempered of the lorde, Prouer. 16 and Capitulo. 18. lootte putes awaye contradyccyon and doth iudge great men, &amp; more of this matter in my boke
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9830:46"/>
of callynge. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> All canones of the worlde can not <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="119"/> lawefullye choſe one byſhoppe of the churche of Ieſu Chryſte. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Kynges and prynces and other <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="120"/> great nobles ought to choſe very ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lerned men in the worde of god, whiche ſhulde be byſhoppes in theyr courtes, and ſhulde teache theyr cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyers oft the moſt pure worde of god.</p>
               <p>☞Yf one, or two, or mo houſes of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="121"/> faythfull perceyue that they haue not faythful byſhoppes ſuffred to them, or the people of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> peryſhe wyl not choſe euaungelycall men, they maye pryuat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye take them ſelues aproper byſhope or paſtor. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Thoſe ſhulde alonely be choſen <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="122"/> byſhoppes that be ſuche as Paule de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrybethe. 1. Tymothe. 3. and Tyte. 1. that is to be irreprehynſyble with out faute kepynge hoſpetalyte, gentyl, ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, iuſte, meke, holy, huſbandes of one wyfe, in feare and care of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernynge theyr owne houſe, hauynge childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lerned with al chaſtyte, which be not proude, couetous, drunkerdes, angrye, contencyous, but honeſt, able
<pb facs="tcp:9830:47"/>
in worde and ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ners wel to order the churche of god, and theyr wyues muſt be chaſte honeſt, ſober, and faythful in all thynges. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="123"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Yf any of the cetize<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nobles be ſuch one he may be choſen byſhope of the congregacyon notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng all the decrees of the apoſtate kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. ☞ ☞ ☞ ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="124"/> ☞ It is heryſye and folyſhnes to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme that the aforeſayde texte of the apoſtle, of the wyfe and chyldren, is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwayes vnderſtande (as the enne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myes of mekenes do ſaye) them of a lawefull wyfe and chyldren naturally begotten in matrymonye. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="125"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Therfore maryed men maye be made byſhoppes and preache openly the worde of god, and after the pure texte of the apoſtle, there ought none to be choſen byſhoppe of the congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacyon, excepte he be maryed or haue bene or wyll be. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="126"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: And for that cauſe god wolde that all, except a fewe prophetes, apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and byſhopes, ſhulde haue be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryed, and ſhulde be to this daye, that there be no ſuſpeccyon of whormon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynge
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:9830:47"/>
or vnclenlynes, and that they myght more ſafly be conuerſante with other. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Alſo by an other reaſon that they <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="127"/> myght be partakers of holy matrymo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye, that ought to preach the hye my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes of it, the which be in Chryſte &amp; the churche, for what be all the ſcryp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of god, but ſermones of hys my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteryes, and hys churche. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>☞ They that haue choſen byſhopes,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="128"/> where as cauſe is, maye lawefully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe them. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A iuſt cauſe of depoſycyon of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="129"/> ſame is vnſyncere preachynge of the worde of god .i. yf they myxte lawes, decrees, and tradycyons of men, with goddes ordynaunce. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Deacons of the churche, be thoſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="130"/> that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythful choſe, for to gather, &amp; dyſtribute to the pore, the almes of the faythful, whiche nowe many cetyes of Germanye do, makynge comen boxes for it, ſuch were the <hi>.7.</hi> deacons electe and inſtytute of the apoſtles at hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, of whom Stephen the Marter was one. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>:</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Men of good wytnes, faythful, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="131"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:48"/>
maryed muſte be choſen deacons <hi>.1.</hi> Tymothe. <hi>3.</hi> whiche if they be pore let them be ſuſteyned with the comen al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes by the decree of the churche.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="132"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The churche of god hath no my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters beſydes theſe byſhoppes and deacons for byſhoppes, preſtes, dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, ſubdeaco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. of the kyngdome of the pope, be deacons of men, ordy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned without tyſtymonyes of the word of god. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>☞ Of punyſhment and puttynge out falſe byſhoppes and falſe apoſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les from the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion of the faytheful. Capit. 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="133"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>L prophiſye and ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture of god is profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table when it is ſynce rely teached, &amp; hande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led. Tymothe. 3. for it is a openynge of the ſpirite of truthe, to the helthe of the faythfull. 1. Corinth. 12.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="134"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For it is the worde of the wyſdome of god, more precyous then golde and ſyluer, and to whom all that can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyred
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:9830:48"/>
maye not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared Pro. 3. nor precyous ſtone maye not be aſſymulat to it, and all treſure is counted but as cley in the ſyght of it. Sapien. 1. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Prophane doctryne, and ſtraunge <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="135"/> from god doth not profyte, but alway to the greater wykydnes, and dothe waſte, crepe, and conſume, euen as the dyſeaſe of canker. 2. Tymoth. 2. for it it Leuen ſone corrupting al the dowe 1. Corin. 5. and Galat. 5. and euell co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munycacyon deceyueth, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tythe. 1. Corinthy. 5. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Suche maner of wyked ſermones &amp; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="136"/> contrary to truthe, be teached, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued alonlye of them that be corrupted in mynde. 1. Tymo. 6. and .2. Tymo. 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Yf he ought to be taken from the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="137"/> myddes of the faythfull, neyther it be not lawfull, to accompanye with hym that is called brother .i. faythfull, that with his ſynne offendythe the congre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gacyon of god, moche more he that with hys wyked teachynge turnythe the people from Chryſte, <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> An heretyke after the thyrde mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhyon,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="138"/> repugnynge to the truthe, is to be flede as a banyſhed man Tyte. 3.
<pb facs="tcp:9830:49"/>
and not bryngynge the pure worde of god, he is not to be receyued into your houſe, nor you ought not to ſalute him for he that ſalutyth him conſentys to hys euell deades. 2. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. canonycal.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="139"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Furthermore as euery good man of the houſe ought to rule hys houſe, ſo kynges prynces, and rulers theyr lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſubiecte to them. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> : ☜ ☞</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="140"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Therfore euen as good men of the houſes ought to put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr houſes, and punyſhe falſe prophetes and here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tykes, not bryngynge the doctryne of Chryſte, ſo kinges prynces and rulers fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr proper landes and lordſhyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes, theſe be bounde to this, leſt theyr proper houſes be deceyued and mayde ſtraunge from Chryſt. Alſo the other for helthe of theyr ſubiectes. : <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="141"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> And for that cauſe of the beſt kyngꝭ haue ſlayne falſe prophetes, the lorde commaundynge. Deutri. 15. he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth falſe prophetes, and fayners of dreames, whiche turne hys people from hym, to be ſlayne. :¶:¶:¶:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="142"/> ☞ Yf that as is open in many places of ſcrypture, offences muſte be taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amonge the myddes of the people
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:9830:49"/>
of the lorde, thoſe verely are chefely to be taken away that dyſtroye ſoules of whom falſe preachynge is chefe.</p>
               <p>☞All preachyng of the kyngdome of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="143"/> the pope is deceyuable and admyxte with lyeng, therfore it muſt be fled as the poyſon of Aſpys incurable. Alſo all preachers of the ſame kyngedome bycauſe they be falſe prophetes and falſe apoſtles nat borne and ſente of god, but of fleſſhe and blode. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Therfore this moſte pryncypally <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="144"/> of all them that rule muſte be lokyd on that true byſhopes .i. true euangelyſtꝭ of the worde, gouerne well people ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iecte to them in the ſame worde. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Let them expulſe falſe byſſhopes .i.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="145"/> falſe prophetes from theyr landes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the thyrde moniſhyon, except they amende. and if they affyrme that they haue the worde of god and the quicke voyce of god as ſome ſay, lete them be ſuffred to do what they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, vntyl they be prouyd of them that haue the moſte pure worde if it be of god or nat, and as it is knowen nat to be of god, lette all prynces banyſhe them theyr lorde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyppes / and ſo do with falſe prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb facs="tcp:9830:50"/>
that ſprynge dayly. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="146"/> ¶ For who that of right wytte wyl de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nye, kynges, prynces, and rulers to be bounde to that, to ſeke peace, &amp; helthe of theyr people, and to exyle from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all what ſo euer dothe alyenat them from god. ☜☞: ☜: ☞: ☜☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="147"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> And I doure nat but it is lawful for them by the forſayde chapi. Deute. 13. whiche is reuocate in no place to ſlee them, when they perceyue that they turne theyr people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inmaculat ſcriptures of god, to the ſacralegious decrees of the kyngdome of the pope, and other inuencions of men, for they haue the ſworde. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="148"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Dyd Helyas erre whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſlewe. 858. prophetes aſwell of Baalle as other places. 3. Reg. 18. and Iehu whiche dyd ſlee the prophetꝭ and worſhypers of Baalle. 4. Regum. 10. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="149"/> ¶ But I do nat affyrme this to be ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſarye to chryſten prynces, that all thoughe as I haue ſayde, they ſhulde be ſeperat and expulſyd from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, vndoutidly it is neceſſary, or els the gylty men of ſo many ſoules as haue ben deceyuyd of this prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:9830:50"/>
of antichryſt, ſhulde peryſhe, I do rather counſel and wolde alwaye that they ſhulde be banyſhed then ſlayne / for they maye amende. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> In caſe you obiecte thoſe that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyp <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="150"/> the pope. to be countyd for mere gentyles, and therfore to ſuffre the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue theyr doctoures and prophetes, we anſwere that it is nat lyke reaſon, for they wyll be taken for the faythful of Chriſte and the other wyll nat.</p>
               <p>Forthermore there is one doctryne of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="151"/> the faythful y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> moſt pure worde of god with whiche they muſte be gouernyd.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Therfore they that be of the king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="152"/> of the pope, if they couyt to be ſauyd, muſte cleaue to the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple worde of god, the inuencyons of menne ſet-aparte. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Nor it is nat trewe (that ſome ſay)<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="153"/> that it is lawful to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſant with bretherne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be reproche to the chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, and falſe prophetꝭ, as it were with true gentyles, as you may perceyue of ſcryptures aforſayde. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> They that attayne to the kingdome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="154"/> of the pope wyl be taken for bretherne i. faythfull, and theyr falſe apoſtles,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:51"/>
for euangelyſtes of Chryſte. For vnder the cloke of Chriſte and hys moſte holy worde, they bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g deceyuyd craftely ſtryue againſte bothe Chriſte and his worde. they are to be fledde of all faythfull, and of prynces and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers to be extyncte. leſte they preache or affyrme any ſuche thynge or els to be taken away and banyſhed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panye of the faythefull. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="155"/> ¶ Nor it is nothynge materyall that ſome ſay, there ſhulde no man be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynyd to faythe, for that is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande alonly of gentyles, that do pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe them ſelues ſtrange from Chriſt, the other wyll be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyd for faythful.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="156"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> It is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to the purpoſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome ſay, ſo they ſhulde be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pellyd to ypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryſye. Verely they be nat excomuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate or confoundyd that they ſhulde be made ypocrytes, but they ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundyd of ypocrytes maye be made true chriſtyanes and if they wyll tary in ypocriſy it ſhalbe imputed to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="157"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Dyd Paule ſynne, commaundyng a certayne man to be excomunycate, and taken fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the myddes of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful. 1. Cor. 5. if he had nat ben conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyd
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:9830:51"/>
but in to hypocryſye, myght it the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue be ſayde that Paule and the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panye of the Corinthians had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellyd hym to hypocryſy. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </p>
               <p>☞ Therfore, we conclude that euery <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="158"/> man ought to banyſhe from his houſe and prynces frome theyr landes falſe apoſtles nat wyllyng to amende, leſte Chriſte be teachyd dyuerſly and / his worde beleuyd to be dyuerſe, wherof Chriſte may be deuyded in his people and by thys dyuerſytye all places be troubled. ☞ <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶Therfore it is laufull for byſhopes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="159"/> and the people of the faythfull, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre theyr prynces, and rulers to be ca<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>refull amongeſtes them all, and to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell falſe prophetes frome theyr lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des that the pure worde of god maye be teachyd in euery place. ¶: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: ¶</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> And if they that rule be enemyes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="160"/> of truthe, and wyll nat here the worde ſufferyng them to be deceyuyd, of the prophetes of antychriſte and monkes (as is theyr propertie) excepte they amende ſurely they ſhall peryſhe.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> And if they couyt to be ſauyd, lette <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="161"/> them here the worde of the lorde, and
<pb facs="tcp:9830:52"/>
that moſte dylegentlye, and lette them pray the lorde, that he wyll vouchſafe to lyghten them with his ſpirite. For then they prayeng in faythe god wyll make open his trewethe. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="162"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>It is dampnable that many ſay they wyll folowe the maners and faythe of theyr predyceſſours, for this ſacryle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyous ſayng dothe peryſhe many. As I haue ſpoken in the boke of the cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blyndnes. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the prologue.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="163"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> wo be to wycked prynces and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers that for the decrees of antychriſt denye the veryte of Chriſte, and do en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pryſone, ꝑſecute, and ſlee hys louers. Verely they are madder and worſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Nero or Diocleſiane, and al other tyrannes. For they dyd perſecute and denye that they knewe nat. Verely theſe blynder then blyndnes it ſelfe. Call them ſelues Chriſtes ſeruauntes and loue hys worde, &amp; yet they denye and treade downe bothe Chriſte and his worde, and receyue for him donge of inuencyons of men, and worſhyppe for Chriſte antichriſte and his lawes, this euery man perceyueth excepte he be blynde as they be. O I wolde to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:9830:52"/>
God the lorde wolde ſende another Ioſy as that wolde dyſtroy all greate buldynges, places, aulters, phaanes, ſecres, decrees, of antychriſte and all that belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth to that curfyd worſhyp 4. Reg. 23. and. 2. Parali. 34. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> In what thynges byſſhoppes of the churche of God, ſhulde be ſubiecte to prynces and ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers and of theyr auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toryte, and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſtery that is of the worde and ſacramentes, and of ſentwaryes. The ſeuenthe Chapitre. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Yſhoppes .i. mynyſters <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="169"/> of the worde / be in all thynge ſubiecte to pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and rulers as other cytezyns be, excepte in theſe thynges that be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>longe to theyr propre offyce. For it is neceſſarye that they be cytezyns whiche we adfyrme of all relygyouſe. ☞ <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:53"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="165"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Byſhoppes in mynyſtery of the worde be ſubiecte to no man but god a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lone, &amp; iudgement of the churche, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che dothe iudge by the worde of god.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="166"/> ☞ If lordes probybyte preachyng to byſhopes, for a day or .ij. they muſt be obeyd, but perpetually obey them nat for god muſt rather be obeyd the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man. Actes .5. If they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde they ſhall interprete the worde of god agaynſte hys propre nature, that is after the wyl of the pope &amp; his kyngdome, obey them nat, but reſyſte the mater more purely and feruently. ☞ <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="167"/> ¶ And they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde that they ſhal teache tradycyons and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of men, obey them nat, and ſo of al other of this maner, that be agaynſte the worde of the lorde. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="168"/> ☞ The greatyſt and hyeſt poynte of theyr offyce, is to preache to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, thoſe thynges that the lorde hath ſpoken ſo purely, ſo nakydly, and ſo ſymply, as god ſaythe, nother increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge, nor demynyſhyng .i. puttyng to nothynge of the inuencyons and drea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for the people of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:9830:53"/>
ſhuldbe rulyd by the alonly worde of the lorde. ☞ <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Theyr auctorite is, to correcte with <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="169"/> the worde of god, ye kynges and pryn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces and rulers, and with the church to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gyther to ſeperate apoſtates, and ſlan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derers of the worde fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the comunion of the faythfull, and they ſo amending to receyue them agayne.</p>
               <p>☞ It is alſo aparte of theyr offyce,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="170"/> chefly in thoſe dayes, that the chylde of perdycyon the man of ſyn, is to be publyſhed to the electe with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirite of the mouthe of the lorde .i. with hys worde, leſt they conſentyng to him do peryſhe, to expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to al people, with a quicke voyce and wrytyng, thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces of ſcrypture perteynynge to that kyngdome, euery man as he hathe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the lorde, let hym be banyſhed from the temples of god, that is frome the hertes of the faythful, and let him neuermore be taken of them, for the vycker of god, or ſpouſe of the church for if he be to be reuelid with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of the lorde, it is neceſſary that it be done fyrſte &amp; pryncypally by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god hathe made his euangelyſtes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:54"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="171"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> But I do nat denie this to belonge to all faythefull that haue the worde of god, for it is commaundyd to all men of the kyngdome of the pope, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſimilitude of the whore of Ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bylon mother of al fornycacyon. Apo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>calyp. 18. Go from her my people and be nat parttakers of her ſynnes, by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe her ſynnes haue come to heuyn and the lorde remembrethe her iniqui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ties, gyue her as ſhe hathe gyuen to you, and double her double workes, in the cuppe that ſhe dyd myxe to you myxte to her double, as muche as ſhe hathe gloryfyed her ſelfe in delycates ſo muche gyue to her tormente &amp; mour<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nynge. whiche wordes I haue expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyd in the preface of myne oracyon in to the rule of the mynorytes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="172"/> ¶ Therfore nother emperoure kyngꝭ nor prynces, or any other rulers, may lawfully prohybyte that theſe thyngꝭ ſhulde nat be done, and if they do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hybite they ought nat to be obeyd, for God is more than manne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ormes and rotennes. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="173"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> They may forbyd that any thyng ſhulde be done without the worde and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:9830:54"/>
then they are to be obeyed. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>☞ And they may conſtrayne .i. leſte <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="174"/> any man robbe or ſtrike the popes cha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plens, and monkes / or of hys owne brayne plucke downe ydolles, for this belongeth to prynces and rulers, that haue the ſworde, that if any thynge muſte be done, it may be done with hol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſome counſel, and in good tyme by the worde of god. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> For all that the companye of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="175"/> faythfull gatheryd and well enformyd in the worde of god, may for this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, deſyre and that inſtantly prynces and rulers, that all thyng may be done peſably, ordinatly and in good ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>¶ wherfore meſſengers that is apoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="175"/> and byſhoppes of god, be ſubiecte alonly to god i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miniſtery of the worde we ſay in mynyſtery of the worde, for as for al outwarde thyngꝭ, as to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che in thys place rather then in that place, with a ſurplyce or without, in tabernacles of the faythfull, and nat in the comen market or in the market and nat in the tabernacles, and ſo of all other outwarde thynges by which theyr mynyſterye is nat lette, they be
<pb facs="tcp:9830:55"/>
ſubiecte to prynces &amp; rulers as other cytyzens be. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="177"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For and cauſe lawfull be they may, holſom counſell taken, depryue, putte them forthe, and pryſon them. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="178"/> ☞Nat withſtandynge the decrees of the ſonne of perdicyon, whiche vnder payne of curſynge, do prohybyte leſte any man touche his tyrannes and my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters of hys clergye, for what wyll ſuche preceptes, but to wyll that with out any lette, they may waxe wanton, ſtele, and go madde. Forthermore I haue ſayde that god turnythe all the curſyng of this kyngedome of perdy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon to his electe in to a louyng bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="179"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Alſo all ſanctuaryes, pryuyleges and pardones, of that kyngedome be lyes of the deuyll, and therfore to be countyd for nought. ¶: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: ¶</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="180"/> ☞ Therfore bothe byſhoppes, and al other if they haue offendyd maye be taken from any place, ye frome taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles and churcheyardes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="181"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Townes and places may be ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, of prynces and rulers, in whome they that flee, whiche by chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, with
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:9830:55"/>
out hate or malyce haue ſhedde blode, maye be ſafe, vnto theyr innocencye knowen they maye retourne to theyr owne. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>who ſo euer with ſworde, ſtaffe, or <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="182"/> ſtone, or any other way of hate, or ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng in wayte hathe ſtryken or ſlayne any man, he ought nat to be ſuffered ſafe in any place, but alonly he that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaynſt his wyl hath done any of theſe. And ſo the lorde hathe ordeyned cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes for them that flee. Numeri. 35.</p>
               <p>¶No byſhop hathe aucthoryte, vpon <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="183"/> hys felowe, but to teache hym, if he knowe the truthe better, for the fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of archbyſhoppes is nat of the worde of god.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Byſhoppes haue no nede to be <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="184"/> conſecrate of any man, but of the holy ghoſte, it is ſuffycyent to them for all conſecracyon to be ſende and callyd of the lorde.</p>
               <p>☞ If any byſhoppes in them ſelues <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="185"/> theyr wyues, or with dyuers conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſacyon, offende the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon they ought to be correcte of rulers and the churche, and nat geuyng place to hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
<pb facs="tcp:9830:56"/>
doctryne ought to be depoſed of them and ſeperate the comunyon of the faythefull.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="186"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Another mynyſtery of theyres is to baptyze, to miniſter the table of the lorde and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forthe them that amende.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="187"/> ☞ Thys mynyſterye of ſacramentes whiche is but accydent to them, and not pryncypall, they may commyt to other, when they be let with miniſtery of the worde. they be nat ſende to bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyze, but to preache. As Paule ſayeth of hym ſelfe. 1. Cor. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="188"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>To the fyrſte offyce that is to prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chyng be inſeperably knyt, viſitacyon and comfortyng of the ſycke, alwayes that they can to helpe the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon that euery byſhope rulythe in the worde of god.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="189"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Byſhoppes ſhulde nat wayte to be callyd to the howſes of the faythefull, where as they knowe neceſſyty, but of theyr ſelues ſhulde watche and haſte to brynge them helpe and comforthe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9830:56"/>
               <head>The eyght Chapitre. ¶That byſhoppes may nat be lordes and prynces, and it is agaynſte theyr offyce. The eyght Chapitre. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Yſhoppes be nat lordes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="190"/> ouer the people of god but mynyſters and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>☞ Nor they may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="191"/> them nothyng of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues, although they may reproue, deſyre, and blame, in all pacyence and pure doctryne of the ſcriptures of god. 2. Timoth. 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> It is nat out of pacyence, but a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="192"/> neceſſarye and moſte free zele to god, when any man is angrye and feruent agaynſte the wycked, after the worde of the lorde, for verely there muſte be reſyſtence with the worde as ofte as neceſſyte requyryth, ye with the moſte feruent zele. As Phinees dyd pleaſe with the zele, ſleyng bothe Zambri ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitayne of the trybe of Symeon, and
<pb facs="tcp:9830:57"/>
Cozhi doughter of Sur the prynce of Madianites. Numeri. 15. And alſo Mathathias with that zele. ſleynge a Iue and the meſſenger of the kynge of Antioche, the fyrſte boke of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabeus the ſeconde Chapitre. Lyke wyſe Helias whoſe ſermones were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyn as fyre or a burnynge bronde. 1. Kynges. 17. and Eccleſiaſti .48. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Byſhoppes may nat be prynces and lordes of any place, but of theyr owne howſholde. for it is contrarye to be a byſhope and a prynce. For to be a by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe is to be a mynyſter and faythe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full ſeruande.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="194"/> ¶ Therfore they ought nat to haue lordeſhyppe, of the leaſte towne of all the worlde, the ſauyour ſpekyth to by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes. Matthewe the .20. chapitre and Marke the .18. Chapitre. &amp; Luke the .22. Chapitre. Kynges of genty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les haue rule ouer them, and they that haue power be callyd gracyous lordꝭ. but you nat ſo, that is you ſhall nat haue lordſhyppe of other nor ſhal nat haue power in them as prynces. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:9830:57"/>☞ And bycauſe the pope, and his by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopes,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="195"/> with other perteyninge to his kyngedome, do boſte them ſelues, for mynyſters, &amp; ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes, of the church, and neuertheleſſe, wylbe prynces, and lordes, they muſt be depryued al, kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome, and lordſhyppe, whiche to do, it belongeth to prynces, and rulers.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> If that they be of the hye prynces,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="196"/> and wylbe taken for ſuche, and playe the true prynces and to permyte frely holy byſhopp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> of euery congregacyon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> be ſuffred, or els to be put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> other to be choſen, for prynces. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>¶ It is not laweful for byſhoppes, to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="197"/> haue vycars, offycyalles, ſecretaryes, chauncelers, courtes of ſtryfe, &amp; ſuche other. But alonly helpers, for myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery of Sacramentes, as I haue ſayd before. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ For there is no proceſſe, that maye <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="198"/> lawfully be determyned, before him, or hys offycyalles, for this doth belonge to prynces and rulers. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ But it is lawfull for them, to haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="199"/> a ſcrybe of ſermons of truthe, yf they nede or yf they be ſuche, that can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde
<pb facs="tcp:9830:58"/>
the ſcryptures in wrytynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="200"/> ¶ Scrybes and other that be of the councell of Cetyes, and other nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes ordayned of prynces, and rulers, may receyue teſtamentes, and all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of contractes, whiche is not to be ſuffered, to the notaryes of Anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryſt, and hys tyrannes, excepte they forſake Antychryſt and hꝭ kyngdome and be admytted of rulers, or els the coniurynge, of the ſonne of perdycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuldbe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed, which by al meanes after the worde of god, is to be abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſſhed, and drounke of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the moſte harde cuppe. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="201"/> ☞ To prynces, and rulers, it belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to ſubuerte all pompe, &amp; tyranny, of byſhoppes, and to reforme them to humylyte, and ſymplecyte of apoſtles</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="202"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>Therfore to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope, and cardynals and byſhopes, or other tyrannes, of hꝭ kyngdome, ſhuld not be ſuffered pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyous intereſtys of cetyes, precyous miters, croſſes, hattꝭ, ſlyppers, of ſylke and gyltyd, and rynges, for yf he wyll playe, the byſhoppe let hym enter lyke a byſhoppe, apoſtle, and paſtor, and let it be ſuffycyent for euery one of them,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:9830:58"/>
to haue on, or two, or thre ſeruauntes, for they be not greater then Peter, or Paule, or other apoſtles, whiche haue gone very ofie, with one dyſcyple a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone to the mynyſterye, of the worde, to whoſe humylyte both the pope, car<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynalles, and all the tyrantes of hys kyngedome ought to be reſtored, but what counſel theſe kinges, and lordes that haue admitted thoſe dygnytes of Antychryſte, with theyr honour maye vſe. I haue ſpoken of in the epyſtele to the noble prynce, Iohan cardynall of lotherynge. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Of a brogatyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of fyrſt frutes, tythes, offeringes, and what the faythful owe to theyr byſhopes .i. to true myniſters of the worde, and of thoſe they owe to prynces and rulers. Capitulo. 9.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or mynyſters of the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="203"/> lawe that is to ſaye pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes and leuytes, god hathe ordyned tythes, fyrſte frutes, and oblaty<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ons, of tythes, and fyrſt frutes. Exodi. 20. Leuiticum, the laſt Numeri. 18. and Deutri. 14. of obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyons.
<pb facs="tcp:9830:59"/>
Exodi. 23. and .34. thou ſhalte not apere voyde in my ſyght, and Deu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terono .16. he ſhall not apere voyde before the lorde. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="204"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Verely ons before the lawe Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd gyue tythes to Melchiſeadech kynge, and preeſte of the hyeſte god. Geneſis .14. and Iacobe vowyd to the lorde that he wold gyue tythes of all that he ſhulde receyue. Gene. 28. whiche no doute of, was not without the counſell of the holye gooſte that they bothe dyd. ☞ :<g ref="char:cross">✚</g>:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="205"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Therfore to gyue tythes, that is a good thynge, bycauſe it dothe agree with holy ſcryptures. :<g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="206"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> But we finde in no place, that euer it was lawefull to any man to requyre them of deuty, except the forſayd my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſters of the lawe, and kynges of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raell, as is manyfeſt .1. Regum. 8. of the lawe of a kynge that ſhuld raygne apon them. :<g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: :<g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: :<g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="207"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> For that cauſe the preeſthode of Aaron is abrogate, and is tranſlatyd into Chryſte, and the faythfull, and chriſte is made alone the true and hye byſhoppe of the faythful, as is openly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:9830:59"/>
declaryd in the epyſtle of S. Paule to the hebrues. ☞: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>¶ wherfore byſhoppes, and preſtes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="208"/> of the kyngedome of the pope, be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge leſſe then that whiche they affyrme them ſelues to be. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>:</p>
               <p>¶Nor they do nat ſuccede to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="209"/> of tythes, fyrſt frutes, and oblacyons, whiche be dewe alonly to them afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde, for they be not preſtes, and leui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of the lawe. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>¶ They be therfore execrable theues,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="210"/> when they requyre tithes, fyrſt frutes and oblacyons. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For they be dewe to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by no lawe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="211"/> not by goddes lawe, as I haue ſayde, nor by mannes lawe, for all ſuche lawe dothe not bynde the faythful. bycauſe it is wyked, brynginge them into bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of the lawe, that god hathe made free from it. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Alſo Chryſte ſpekynge of tythes.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="212"/> Mathewe .23. and Luke .11. ſpekethe in the pretertens, you ought to haue done theſe. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. that you maye knowe they ſhulde haue be gyuen them, and not you. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ And yf you ſaye they ſhulde haue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="213"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:60"/>
be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Ergo nowe, you conclude foliſhlye, becauſe the lawe is abrogat, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it ſhuld folowe that you ſhuld haue be cyrcumſyſyd, offeryd beaſtes, go to Hieruſalem on dayes apoynted of the lorde, Ergo nowe, yf thys con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequente be nought nor the fyrſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="214"/> ¶ Furthermore althoughe faythfull be not bounde to gyue thoſe thynges to them, yet rather then they ſhulde ſtryue, they ſhulde haue them at theyr requeſte accordynge to that of Luke. 6. fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him that taketh away thy cloke, do not forbyde thy coote, to all that axythe the geue, and of hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that taketh from the, axe it not agayne. ☞</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="215"/> ¶ They maye, ye they ought, yf they maye do it, to warne them leſte they wyll peryſhe, for ſuche a deteſtable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actyon, and thefte, for it is wytten yf thy brother offende the, correcte hym. Matthewe .18. and Luke .17. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="216"/> ¶ But it is the duety of princes, and rulers, to make people free, from thys thefte, and tyrannye of the apoſtate kyngedome, for nother the pope, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynalles, nor byſhoppes, nor all they to gether y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> do attayne to this wyked
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:9830:60"/>
kyngdome, may lawefully requyre one halfepenye, vnder the name of fryſte frutes, tythes, and oblacyons. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Let theſe flowe belyes worke, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="217"/> lyue with laboure, and lette them haue wherof they may gyue to rhe pore his neceſſite, as is wrytten in the ſweat of thy browes, thou ſhalt eate thy breade Gene. 3. and .2. Theſſal. 3. he that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boryth not let not hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eate, and yf they be of the houſes of prynces, or nobles or any other ryche men, lette them go to theyr owne houſes, &amp; do ſumthyng els better prouydyd, ſo that they do not ſteale other mennes gooddes and maye be ſauyd. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ To true byſhopes .i. to true euaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelyſtes,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="218"/> be not owyd fyrſte frutes, ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, and oblacyons, but alonly they, to whome they preache, be bounde to helpe them, and theyr houſeholde, as you maye openly ſe in many places of ſcrypture, as I haue teached in an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place more largelye. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ For it is ſayde cheffelye to them,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="219"/> wyl not you to heape treaſure. Math. 6. and although thꝭ chaunce to al men yet they ſhulde gyue example to other
<pb facs="tcp:9830:61"/>
that they maye ſhewe Chryſte, and hꝭ mekenes yee in theyr deades. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="220"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Therfore &amp; yf they haue any thyng plentyfully geuen to them, lette them geue it to the pore, and let them kepe hoſpytalyte as Paule ſaythe. Tite. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="221"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> wherfore vnder the goſpell there is none that of the apoyntmente of god, tythes ſhulde ſpecyallye be gyuen to, not the kyngedome of the pope, as we haue ſayde, nor yet true euaungelyſtꝭ to whome euen by the comaundement of god, meate, and drynke, and clothe, is dewe of them whom they rule, with the worde and not to prynces, rulers or nobles. ☞: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="222"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For to them muſt be gyuen tributes and cuſtomes, by the precept of chriſt Matth. 22. Marke. 12. Luke. 20. gyue that to the Emperour, that is the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peroures, &amp; that, to god that is godes and Roma. 13. gyue to euery one theyr deutye, to whom trybute, gyue trybute to whome cuſtome, gyue cuſtome, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> honor, giue honor, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dread, dreade, &amp; wolde god that many iniuſte exactyons were taken away, and that they wolde take alonly tythes, as the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:9830:61"/>
lorde dyd apoynte the kynges of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael. 1. Regum. 8. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Alſo they muſt haue tythes, twelftꝭ <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="223"/> twentytes, and ſuche other lawefull cuſtomes, whiche many haue purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd by laweful meanes, as geuynge for them, and theyr heyres, theyr proper landes, for a perpetual cuſtome of the fyftenth, or twelfte ꝑte of theyr frutes</p>
               <p>¶ I do not vnderſtande of vſurus <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="224"/> bergens, for it is wrytten, lende one to another truſtynge of no auauntage. Luke. 6. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> what ſhall then be of tythes, ſhall <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="225"/> they be vtterly put downe, godforbyd but I ſaye that the faythfull be free, that they geue nothynge ouer them, to them whome the man of ſynne com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundethe to be geuen.: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ I geue thꝭ counſel to the faythful,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="226"/> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> of al they that receyue of the lord, to gather tythes, and dyſtrybute them into good vſes, as to helpe the publike weall, to noryſhe true byſhoppes, that truly gouerne, to helpe the fatherles, puples, and wydoes, with other pore.</p>
               <p>¶ we ſaye this of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that be able, for <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="227"/> if they be pore, let them pay nothynge
<pb facs="tcp:9830:62"/>
or els that whiche they maye frely, chefly for a comon weall, &amp; mynyſters of the worde of whome the greatteſt count muſte be gyuen. 1. Tim. 5. ſeny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours that gouerne well be worthye double honoure, chefly they that la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure in the worde and lernynge.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="228"/> ¶ Pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, rulers, and nobles, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as I ſayd) trybutes, &amp; other ſhuldbe gyuen by the lawe, maye not thynke them free to do with them what they wyll, for they muſte be watchynge for a good ſtate, and peaſe of the people, and be meke, and plentyful to the pore</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="229"/> ¶ To whom thys muſt be counſyled, that by example of Abraham, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sayntes, to dyſtrybute tythes of all that they receyue, to the pore, and not to ſet vppe chappels and buylde cloyſtures. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="230"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Nor it is not lawefull for them to multeplye horſes, for pride, to haue many wyues, or hores, to gether great heapes of golde, &amp; ſyluer to be proude ouer hys brethren that is, people who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhulde haue in ſteade of hꝭ brethren to declyne from truthe, and iuſtyce, to the ryght hande, or to the lefte hande,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:9830:62"/>
but they ſhal haue the lawe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lord, in whiche they ſhal rede, all the dayes of theyr lyfe, and lerne to dreade the lorde, and theyr god, and kepe hys pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptes, as is ſayde in. Deutryno. 17.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the table of the lorde that it is not a ſacrefyce, and of wyked and vſurus cuſtomes of the kingdome of perdy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon vtterlye to be pluckyd awaye and of purgatory. Capi. 10.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He pope and hys ſcoles <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="231"/> haue dyffyned the table of the lord, to be a ſacry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyſe, and haue denyed in it to be the promyſe of grace, and both kyndes to be giuen to any other then hys chaplens, whiche be all he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſye, becauſe they repugne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> textes of ſcripture, for if you loke apon thoſe that be ſpoken of it. Mat. 26. Marke. 14. Luke. 22. and. 1. Cor. 11. you ſhall pleynly perceyue thys to be the table of god, whiche you maye not ſacrefice, but eate and drynke, and to be the newe Teſtament, of whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptures be inſtrumentes, in whome
<pb facs="tcp:9830:63"/>
the grace of god, and remiſſion of ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is promyſyd, of whome they that beleue be pertakers, and bothe kindes to be gyuen, to all that haue proued them ſelues whether they beleue in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> promeſſe of god, and at the laſte, by thꝭ takynge to ſhewe the lordes deathe, vntyll he come to iudegement .i. to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, &amp; be a memoryal of his death, to them that beleue, for ſo ofte doth he dye to them, with the moſt ſureſt ſigne that is to ſaye, the frute of his deathe is geuen to them, as ofte as they eate thys breade, and drynke thys bloude in faythe. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="232"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> whoſoeuer is pertaker, of this table in fayth, is made a member of Chryſt, and eateth his fleſhe, and drynketh hꝭ bloude Iohan. 6. to the which he that goethe without faythe eateth, &amp; dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his iudgement makynge no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the lordes bodye. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="233"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>To ſerche here more cureouſlye the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſymplenes of the texte wyllyth, is abomynable before the lorde.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="234"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The ſuperſtecyouſnes, is not to be ſuffred, to kepe the breade of the lord, in the tabernacles of the faythfull, it
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:9830:63"/>
was not ordayned of the lorde, to be kepyd ſo or borne aboute ſo po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſlye but that it myght be eaten. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> And for that cauſe lette ſyncere e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaungelyſtes <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="235"/> prouyde that it be not kepyd, for that kepynge is beſyde the order of god, for truly then the breade is to be ſantyfyed, with the worde of god, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is to be taken, what houre ſoeuer it be, and what ſoeuer the here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſye of Antychryſte hathe otherwyſe dyffyned, and we ſaye the ſame of the cuppe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> both muſt be gyuen to gyther</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> we do not ſaye, that this table is to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="236"/> be mynyſtred to chyldren, or they that beleue not, but vtterlye, to all that can beleue in the promyſe of god.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> It is the deuty of byſhoppes to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="237"/> them dylygentlye that they maye knowe what this holy feaſt is, and not to receyue to it, all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> puttes him ſelfe to it, but the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they haue inſtructe, or do not doute, to be well inſtructe.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The hye preparacyon is, that any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="238"/> man beynge thryſtye, or hongry go to it .i. that he confeſſe with al his harte, that he hath nede of the grace of god, and remiſſyon of ſynnes, and beleue to
<pb facs="tcp:9830:64"/>
goddes promyſe that beinge pertaker of this table, he ſhall obteyne hys de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyer by the meryte of the paſſyon of Chriſt, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this feaſt is a memorye</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="239"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Althoughe thys holye feaſt, and alſo baptyſme be moſte ſure ſygnes, to the faythful, of the grace of god to be hade, yet without theſe ſygnes euery faythefull, beleuynge the truthe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyueth the ſame, as apereth in many places of ſcrypture. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="240"/> ¶And for that cauſe it perteyneth to the aboundance of goddes worſhype, that he hathe put theſe ſygnes to the more copyous co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte of the faythful, of whom I haue ſpoken more, cheflye in the boke of the cauſes of the blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Tracta. 5. Capitulo. 7. and. 8</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="241"/> ¶ Auguſtyne, and other ſayntes, and the Mayſter of ſentences. 12. Dyſtyn. 4. do not affyrme thys table to be pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perly a ſacrifyce, but ſo to be called ſo of ſome, bycauſe it is a memorye of a ſacryfyce ones offeryd on the croſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="242"/> ¶ But as the memorye of a thinge is not the thynge, nor the memorye of golde, or a perſon, is not golde or the perſon, ſoo nor the memorye of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryfyce,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:9830:64"/>
is the ſacryfyce. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> It was an execrable faynynge of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="243"/> the deuell, to make of thys ſweteſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, of euerlaſting helthe, a ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce of the kingdome of Antychryſte, wherof is ſpronge vſurye, marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyſe, fayres, and innumerable errores aboute the maſſe, by the whiche innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable haue peryſhed, &amp; ſlowe belyes be fatted and ſette out. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ It is laweful no more to the fayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="244"/> to ſacrefyce Chryſte then to kyll hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but alonly to worſhyppe the memo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye of hys deathe in faythe, in perta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge of hys table.: ☞:</p>
               <p>☞ All that, nowe the truthe openyd <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="245"/> agayne ſacryfyce Chryſte, do alwaye ſynne moſte greuouſlye.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Therfore yf any man in any place <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="246"/> to auoyd y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of many, be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyd to ſay maſſe, let him leaue out al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> that maketh mencyon of a ſacryfyce, pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipally the Cano<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, except the wordꝭ of bu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thꝭ place. <hi>Qui pridie.</hi> &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> And let him take hede, that neyther <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="247"/> for that nor if he haue lefte out any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thynge as the manyple ſtole. &amp;c. that he be prykyd in hys conſcyence,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:65"/>
as for one offence knowynge that the faythful is not bounde to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tradycyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of men, but is free, yet becauſe of the weake theſe outwarde thynges, are not in euery place to be lefte out.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="248"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> whiche yf it make agaynſte thy conſcyence it edefyethe to hell fyer, and yf it folowe a wauerynge conſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſynneth lette hym therfore put away thy wauerynge conſcyence, and for that axe lyghtenynge of the lorde.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="149"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Neyther for quyke, nor for deade it is laweful to offer Chryſte neyther in the ſacrament, nor otherwyſe, for he hathe offered hym ſelfe ones for all.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="250"/> ☞ All foundacyons of maſſes, yeres myndes, cryenge of the quere, and all ſuche, that be done in the kyngedome of the pope, be hylye abhomynable to god beſydes that they be for the more part vſury, what ſo euer the ſon of per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dycyon in a certen wauerynge hathe otherwyſe dyffyned, a thynge vtterly aduerſarye to the worde of god, gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng to hys ſynagoge Chryſt prohy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytythe vſury Luke .6. lende one to a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nother truſtynge for no auauntage, whiche thys man of ſynne hath made
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:9830:65"/>
lawefull / and what is it that he dare not dyffyne agaynſte the immaculate ſcriptures of god, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any thyng may come to the treſorye of hꝭ kyngdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> In a dyſceytfull ſpyryte / and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="251"/> of deuyls / was purgatorye fey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyd as many mo were. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Therof hathe the deceyuynge of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="252"/> the worlde cheflye come / and the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd fayres of the kingdome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> I praye you let the kyngedome of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="253"/> the pope anſwere / from what thynges ſhulde a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be purged to be ſauyd / not alonlye from ſynnes: ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> But alonly by fayth in Chryſt we <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="254"/> be purged from them / and iuſtyfyed / not with fyre / water / ſworde / laboure / or any other externe thynge / nor with the prayers of any ſaynte as I haue proued Luke .1. and Cantico .1.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Althoughe he that is iuſtyfyed of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="255"/> faythe / workethe many good workes / for faythe hathe her ſtrength by loue. Galat. 5. and is neuer ſeperate from good workes / yf it be true.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> If by fyer / y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prayers of other / any <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="256"/> laboure or worke / we be pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yd / and iuſtyfyed / ergo ſuperfluouſly and frely
<pb facs="tcp:9830:66"/>
Chryſte was deade for vs. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="257"/> ¶ Therfore there is no other purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torye / or purgatyon / but that whiche is of faythe in Chryſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="258"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> And they that iudge otherwayes / fynde not one place in the holye / and canonycall ſcryptures / for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="259"/> ¶ For that the .2. Machabe the .12. that Iudas a collatyon mayde, ſende .12. thouſande beyſandes of ſyluer to Hieruſalem, is not of auctoryte / for thoſe bokes of the Machabyes be not cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in the rule of the hebrues / alſo if thou loke dylyge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tlye on that place, thou ſhalt fynde that rather they dyd pray leſt the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of the deade, which they hade taken of the giftes of ydol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les, ſhulde hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, then for the deade men them ſelues, and for that cauſe it is concludyd, that holſome and holye is the thought to pray, for the deade, that they may be loſyd of theyr ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, is agaynſte canonycall ſcryptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="260"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> In ſyght of the lorde the dethe of ſayntes, that is of the faytheful is pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyous, that be iuſtefyed and ſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cryfyed by faythe. Pſalmo. 115. alſo Apoca. 14. Iohan harde a voyce ſayenge to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:9830:66"/>
him bleſſyd are they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dye in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde, that is in the faythe of Chryſte.</p>
               <p>¶ Alſo of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> dye ſo in the lorde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="261"/> the ſpirite ſpekethe that from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forthe they reſte from theyr laboures, and yf they reſte, ergo they ſuffer no fyer Apocal. 14. great is the auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryte of thys place, what ſo euer many other thynke, for it doth dyſſent from no place of other ſcryptures / whiche ſomtyme god wyllynge I ſhall proue.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> The dethe of ſynners .i. of vnfayth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="262"/> is worſte. Pſalmo .33. ſynners be callyd vnfaytheful, bycauſe ſynnes be imputyd to them, and all theyr deades be not of faythe, and therfore they be ſynne. Roma .14. truly faythefull be called iuſte, &amp; ſayntes, bycauſe ſynnes be not imputyd to them for true fayth Pſalmo .31. bleſſyd be they whoſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quites be forgyuen, and whoſe ſynnes be coueryd, <abbr>bleſſyd</abbr> is the man, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the lorde hathe not ymputyd ſynne.</p>
               <p>¶ Furthermore faythfull lazarus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="263"/> deade, he was borne into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of Abraham / verelye the wyked<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynes was buryed quyckely in hell which I haue expounded in my enar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racyon
<pb facs="tcp:9830:67"/>
of Luke. Capitulo. 16. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="264"/> ¶ Therfore bleſſyd is the faythefull dyenge in the lorde, for into hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ſhal ſlepe, and reſt. Pſal. 4. the vnfaythful verelye is accurſyd. ☞: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="265"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> we conclude therfore / that alonlye fayth is our purgatory, bleſſyd is he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo purgyd, dyeth, other purgatory we finde not, for they be moſt lykeſt drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, what ſo euer hath be dyffyned of theſe / thꝭ lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge tyme / nor haue nothing profytyd / but to fat / and ſet out ſlowe belyes of the kyngedome of the pope.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="267"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Therfore bycauſe they were with out the teſtimony, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worde of god / they be wyked, that the forſayde kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of the pope, hath diffined in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and to be plucked awaye of prynces / and rulers, and reformyd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rule of the ſcryptures of god. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Of ſectes of perdycyon, and beggynge. Cap. 11.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="268"/>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Othinge more dampnable, ſythe Chryſte was borne, was brought in, then theſe ſectes of perdicyon, ſectes of perdycyon be they that can not but deſtroy, as be the monaſty call ſectes.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:9830:67"/>¶ Alonly one profeſſion is of helthe,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="269"/> that is to ſaye, to profeſſe Chryſte, whiche bycauſe he hathe, one ſpirite, one faythe, one god, one redemer, one medyator, or aduocate, one worde, one iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, one baptyſme, one teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of grace, dothe hyely abhorre ſcyſmy, and deuyſyon of the thynges that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyne to hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, namely of his only ſpous the churche, for the whiche Paule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prouethe the Corynthyans of theyr zele, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion ſaing I am of Paule I of Cephas, I of Apollo. 1. cor. 1.2. &amp;. 3</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Bycauſe there is, one, and the moſt ſuffycyent rule of all, that beleue the worde of god all monaſtycal ſectes be ſuperfluous, and vnprofytable.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Paraduenture they hurte not, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="270"/> be tollerable to them that truſt not or gyue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nought, verely to them that thynke there is in them, the leſte Iote of perfectyon, iuſtyfycatyon, or effy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacyty vnto helthe, they be more poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then the venym of Aſpys.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For verelye the monaſtycall ſecte <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="272"/> is the well of ypocryſye, the Iakes of enuy, ydlenes, dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>knes, grudges, hate ambyſhon, and of all vnclenlynes, the
<pb facs="tcp:9830:68"/>
doughter of the bloude, ſukker deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynge althynge, and alwaye ſaynge, brynge bryng, an enſacyate depnes of tradycyons of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſtryuynge euen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarye to the worde of god. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="273"/> ¶ Nether kyngedome, lordeſhyppe, landes, cuſtomes, tythes, or any great ryches, beſynes, of marchaundyſe, may lawfully, be permyttyd to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Char<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terhouſe freres, benedictynes celyſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or any other mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they cal poſſeſſyoners, of prynces and rulers.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="274"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Aboue all cloyſtures, theſe ought to be ſubuertyd, for they drawe almoſt all the worlde, with ſtryfe and exacty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to bryng, vp certayne ydle &amp; fatte hogges, and what they do more ouer, I tell not. ☜: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="275"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> But theſe that they call beggers, what do they not ſteale with theyr ym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portunate beggynge, be they not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſte the faythefull, as myſe, be in barnes, in clothes, mothes, in wortes, wormes, beſyde y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, that they be callyd ſo beggers, they wyll fare better then many greate men. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="276"/> ¶ Beggynge is alwaye vnlawefull, and nere thefte, to them that can with
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:9830:68"/>
theyr laboure gette neceſſaryes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Therfore it is not laweful, to gyue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="277"/> any thynge to theſe monkes, bycauſe they ought, and maye eate the laboure of theyr ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and ſeke it with occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patyon, whereby they may lyue, and if they can not, let them lerne, for ſaynte Fraunces commaundyd his, ſo to do.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> For howe ofte are we mouyd i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> holy <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="278"/> ſcripture, that it is neceſſary, to helpe pupylles, the fatherles, wydoes, preſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dyſeaſyd, and other that haue neade, of our goodes as we be able, in no place it is co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundede, or prouyd, that any man ſhulde be made a begger, althoughe to all faythefull true po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertye is neceſſarye. ☞: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Alſo it is more bleſſyd to gyue then <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="279"/> take. Actes. 20. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>¶ So ſaynt Fraunces wyl not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="290"/> monkes begge, but when they can not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theyr labour get neceſſary for lyfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> All monkes &amp; monyalles, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="281"/> they haue not receyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> gyfte of contence are bounde, to put awaye theyr coweles, and to be maryed.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> I wolde not condempne, no I <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="282"/> wolde prayſe the cloyſtures of bothe
<pb facs="tcp:9830:69"/>
kyndes, yf they were ſcolles of the faytheful, in whom they ſhulde be wel inſtructyd, with the alonlye worde of god, and honeſte laboures, and myght frelye go forthe when they wolde, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſhulde alway be better, and more chryſtyanly be conuerſant. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="283"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Monkes &amp; monyalles, that affyrme that they wolde lyue in the lyberty of the goſpell, and do nothyng, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the coule be reiecte or not, wyll lyue without the brydle of them that rule, rore as they dyd before, and part to them gooddes of the cloyſter, to be diſtribute at theyr pleſure, thoſe be no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thyng leſſe, then chryſtyans, and goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers, &amp; they be made of Belzebub Sathan, that is of nought worſe, and moſte hatefull to god. <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="284"/> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Aboue all, the cloyſtures of the Mynorytes ought to be ſcolles of the profeſſyon of the goſpell, for Chryſte commaunded to ſaynt Frauncys, that they ſhulde lyue after, the forme of the holy goſpel, whiche I haue prouyd in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries of theyr rule. Cap. 1.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="285"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Princes and rulers, of theyr offyce ought dylygently to watche, that the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:9830:69"/>
goynge forthe of all cloyſters myght be free, and by al meanes ſo to do, that they whiche yet tary in cloyſters lyue ſubiecte, and be dylygently inſtructyd with the alonlye worde of god, or els what ſhal theſe cloyſters be, but chafe ringe houſes, and bonde houſes of the deuyl theſe laſte. 18. poſytyons, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther belongyng to monaſtycal ſecte, I haue declaryd in my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentarye into the rule of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> minorytes more largely.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>whoſe deutye is to iudge of the voyce of the lernyd / yf he be of god / and by what we be aſſuryd / alſo of wekyd vnyuerſytes. Capi. 12.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T dothe belonge to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="289"/> church of god / to iudge of the voyce of all that teache / yf it be of god / whiche we haue proued openly in other bokes chefly in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cantykles of Solomon / the voyce of my well belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Capitu. 2. and. 5. to what the churche of god is, is declaryd within.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For of the worde of god / they alo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly
<pb facs="tcp:9830:70"/>
can iudge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> haue the ſpirite of chriſt, whoſe deuty is to iudge, of hye thingꝭ 1. Corinthi. 2. ☞: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="288"/> ¶ It is hereſye to affyrme / that the ſpirite of Chryſte is not in the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, for he is in them / and they walke and vnderſtande after hym, by whome they mortifye the deades of the fleſhe and lyue, and crye in hym. <hi>abba Pater.</hi> and he gyuethe a teſtymonye to theyr ſpirite, that they be children, &amp; heyres of god, hayres annexyd with chryſte, he axethe for vs with teres vnable to be ſpoken of, and makyth interceſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſayntes after god, whiche Paule ſpeketh of moſte cepoſlye. Roma. 8.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="289"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Furthermore it is the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowen, that any man iudgethe of the ſpirite, when he goeth aboute hys iudgement, with open teſtimonyes of ſcrypture, for the ſcryptures of god, be the moſte ſureſte teſtimonyes, of the iudgementes of hꝭ ſpirite, as I haue ſayde verye ofte.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="290"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> whiche ſcryptures, who ſo euer de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyeth to be neceſſarye, can no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes affyrme the ſurenes of hꝭ ſayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, bycauſe thoſe alone be the ſure teſtymonyes of god. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>:: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:9830:70"/>¶ Therfore they that be of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="291"/> of god that is to ſay ſymple, and meke yee plowe men, and artyfycers, that ſyncerely beleue in god, and be the ſhepe of chryſt, may iudge, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> voyce of theyr paſtor, yf it be in thoſe doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toures or not. ☞: ☜: ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>:</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Verelye they that be not of that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="292"/> church can not iudge of it, but rather abhore and hate it, bycauſe it is aduer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſarye to theyr ſenſe, that is to ſay, the fleſhe by whiche they be ruled.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For any man to iudge, of the worde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="293"/> it helpeth not, to haue be many yeres, at Parryſe, or other vnyuerſityes, or to haue ſtodyed the tongues, excepte the holye gooſte be preſente.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Vnyuerſyties that haue be of many <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="294"/> yeres, ſtryue clene agaynſt the worde of God. ☞: <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>: ☜: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>☞ Promotyons of deuynes whiche <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="295"/> they hunt for, doth enge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dre nothinge, but pryde, and be full of couetouſnes, and vanyte, and is a certen gentyles maner, for what ſo euer is of goddes worde, yf monye be brought, quyckely there is a tytle grauntyd, and doctou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res neuer teachynge, and ofte tymes
<pb facs="tcp:9830:71"/>
the moſt foles be promotyd, wherfore they be abhomynable to god. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="296"/> ¶ And the lorde forbade hꝭ apoſtles / that they ſhulde be made mayſters. Math. 23. no doute but he wolde haue them mayſters, and teachers of the people .i. that they myght teache hys ſcriptures, but he wolde not that they ſhulde hunt for the vayne and proude tytles, nor wolde not, that they ſhuld teach any thyng, but vnder hꝭ ſeruyce</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="297"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> There is no man almoſte, that tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chethe more vnhappely, the ſcryptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res of god, then theſe pompos bugges and ydolles of the worlde. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="298"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Yf any man be worthye, the myny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterye of god, I wolde counſel, that he ſhulde fyrſte be choſen of other deuy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, mete that he may be ſende to any place, and that the companye of the faythefull ſhulde pray for hym, and yf he haue it, let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gyue to the nedy and pore people, and make them a feaſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordynge to the goſpell, &amp; not as they do nowe a dayes, to gyue cappes, glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, or make greate coſte of feaſtes, to ryche men, and full belyes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame day they begyn to profeſſe the goſpell
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:9830:71"/>
they do openlye agaynſte the goſpell, for in truthe all theſe be abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyon byfore the lorde.</p>
               <p>¶ Yf al cloyſtures of the worlde, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="299"/> withi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or nye to cetyes were, as I ſayd a lytle before, the ſcoles of the worde of god, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſuperſtecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of clothing were not obſeruyd, &amp; mans tradicions for we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſerue both God &amp; Baal, the worde of god, &amp; the worde of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Prynces and rulers, yf they wyll iuſtlye rule, let them take hede aboue <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="300"/> al thynge, that Chryſte maye rule his people, alſo let them make ſcoles in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery place, for chyldren, and maydes, in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they may be wel inſtructe, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the worde of god, and honeſte laboures, &amp; lerne to dreade, &amp; loue, our lorde Ieſu Chryſt, to whom with the father, and the holy goſte, be honour, worſhyppe, and empyre for euer more.. So be it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Of the partes, as they cal it of pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce. Cap. 13.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He partes of holy &amp; true pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="301"/> is not confeſſyon, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trytyon, &amp; ſatyſfaccyon, but the actes of a true peny<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tente of faythe without ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſfaccyon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:9830:72"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="303"/> ¶ whiche be neceſſarye to helthe, but not as ſophyſters ſaye. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> &amp; <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="304"/> True ſatyſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo much as it is i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of Chriſte alonly, can be no perte of penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, nor act of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> penyte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="305"/> 
                  <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> But it is the hyeſt rewarde, which we that beleue ſyncerely in chryſte, haue by hys meryte. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="306"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The inſeperable ſeruaunte of true, and neceſſarye penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, is pure fayth, for theſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſauyour ioyned to gether, ſaynge be penytent, &amp; beleue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="307"/> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> This neceſſarye fayth, is not to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue this or that promiſe, but ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue them all, that we doute in no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſe of god, no not in the leaſte, as is that he ſtedefaſtlye cleaue to goddes promyſe, i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which he hath promyſyd to al faithful grace, &amp; remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes by chriſt, as ofte as they axe it i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faythe, &amp; thꝭ is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we muſt beleue.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="308"/> ¶ True penaunce, can neuer be w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out true fayth, nor ſayth is neuer without grace, and the ſpirite of truthe, &amp; alſo affectyons, and true good workes.</p>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>what true penaunce is.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="309"/> PEnaunce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the kyngdome of the pope preacheth, &amp; teacheth is wy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyd, curſyd, and lyenge to the lorde,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:9830:72"/>
for it is nothinge leſſe then penaunce, and maketh nought but an ypocryte, wherfore we call it falſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> This diffynityo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is moſt colde, penaunce is to lamente ſynnes paſte, and in mornynge not to commyt them agayne. ☞: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: ☜: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶True penaunce is to amende dayly from ſyn, with fayth in Chriſte, by the whiche he ſtedfaſtly beleuyth all ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to be remyttyd to hym by chryſte, and hollye to be gyuen hym to walke, in newenes of lyfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> This dayly amendynge is a curcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyenge of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſhe, and mortyfyeng of it, neceſſarye to all faythefull, whiche chriſte co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundeth to be borne about in name of the croſſe, that with frut, &amp; in veryte we may folowe him .i. to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue moſt purely to him, &amp; folowe him.</p>
                  <p>¶ All the lyfe of a chryſtyan is to be penytent, and beleue in Chriſt, that is to mortyfye dayly and ryſe by chryſt.</p>
                  <p>¶ For a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> altho he be holy, as longe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="301"/> as he is in this lyfe hathe vnſtedfaſte fleſhe reſyſtynge the ſpirite, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he ought to crucyfye it dayly, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be ſubiect to the ſpirite.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9830:73"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="314"/> ¶ All affectyons and all worke with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the ſpirite of god, is fleſhe, and is then crucyfyed, when it is hatyd and ſuppreſſyd. ☞: ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="315"/> ¶ who ſo euer is ſo truly penytent, hath chryſt lyuynge, and reynynge in hym, and therfore is of the kyngdome of chryſt, verely the fleſhe, that is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyſce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, and al worke that is not of the ſpirite of god, is dayly more crucy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed, ſubiecte, and mortyfyed.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="316"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> And who ſo euer is not ſo penytent is an ypocryte, and crucyfyeth chryſt in hym, not wyllynge that he reygne vpon hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, wherby he is not of the kyng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome of chryſt, but of the fleſhe and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde, that lyue, &amp; reygne in hꝭ hart.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="317"/> ¶ Chryſt reygneth in our hart, &amp; ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſythe when we truſt to him, verelye he is crucifyed, and doth not pleaſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we truſt in other, and not in hym.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="318"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The worlde and the fleſhe reygne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they pleaſe, &amp; we truſt to them, they be crucyfyed, and mortifyed, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we repreſſe them, and truſte nothynge to them, but rather hate them, and do not to theyr deſyres.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of true good workes.</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="47" facs="tcp:9830:73"/>A Trewe penitent is neuer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="319"/> trewe goodworkes, for he dothe all thyng in faythe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che ſhulde els be wycked, for al thynge that is nat of faythe is ſynne. Roma. 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> They that be of the coniuryng and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="320"/> kingdome of antichriſt, be neuer truly penitent, or do true good workes, for they do nat lyue and worke of faythe.</p>
                  <p>☞The prophetes of antichriſte, that <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="321"/> they may more lyghtly turne the ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple people fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chiſte, ſay that we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hybyte, faſtynge, prayers, and all good dedes, when we do preache nothynge more then that they ſhulde haue true good workes that is of faythe, for we preache thus, that we be iuſtified alon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by faythe, and ſay that we muſte do god workes, nat to be iuſtified, but to brynge forthe frutes of true fayth, for they be frutes of faythe, that be done in that faythe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> we ſaye that there muſte be good <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="322"/> workes, nat as the kyngedome of the po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e but as Chriſte teachythe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e can nat erre bycauſe Chriſt is truthe, and true doctour of the fayth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:9830:74"/>
verely the pope and euery man is alyer. Pſalm. 115. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="323"/> ☞ They ſay there muſte be good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, after the doctryne of the pope, &amp; other men, wherfore it is nat inpoſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that they ſhulde erre, and therof it folowyth that they be full of hereſies, and made antychriſtes, ſcyſmatykes and apoſtata frome the kyngedome of our lorde Ieſus Chriſte. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="324"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> From who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> leſte we be made ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge, &amp; therof to peryſhe, we be made Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſeruauntes, and be apoſtata frome the kyngdome of that anty chriſte the pope. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="325"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>And who ſo euer is nat made ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g from that ſame kyngdome, is a ſciſma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyke from Chriſte apoſtata, and anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte, and at the laſte ſhall peryſhe for euer. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☞</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>Of lybertye and ſubiectyon of the faythefull.</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="326"/> THe faythful dothe alway worke well for he dothe all thynge in faythe, and lybertie of the holy ghoſte. If he eate or drynke, or do any other thynge, he dothe all in the glory of Chriſte, or els in faythe,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:9830:74"/>
or in hys name whiche be all one. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> This lybertie is nat that they may <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="327"/> thynke it free to do any thynge, but that they may knowe that it is moſte fre to them to do thoſe thynges that they be commaundyd by the worde of god, ye and all the men of the worlde wolde commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de otherwyſe, for they be free from all doctrynes and trady<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyons of men, that do nat agree with the worde of god, as be the decrees of the kyngedome of the pope and doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne of ſophiſters.</p>
                  <p>¶ The lybertye of the ſpirite, is nat <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="328"/> carnall, but ſpirituall, and moſte holy, makynge a man free frome all lawe of men, that he is bounde to none except it agre with the ſcriptures of god.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> Alſo as you may ſe of Paule to the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="329"/> Rom<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. &amp; Galath. it makyth a man free from the lawe of god, euyn that ſpirite nat that we ought nat to kepe the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptes of god, nat that we ſhulde kepe them nowe by compulſyon, as before the ſpirite be there, but with the moſte redy wyll. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>☞ Thys lybertie makyth a man ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="330"/> without hypocryſy, the louer of
<pb facs="tcp:9830:75"/>
of truthe, plentyful, ful of charity, and moſte full of all good workes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="331"/> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> For then a man is ſo made free in Chriſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wyl be ſubiecte to euery humane creature for Chriſte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="332"/> ☞ He is curſyd and execrable to the lorde, who ſo euer vnder the name of chriſten lybertie dothe gyue hym ſelfe to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>burynges, drunknes, and ſuche other. for verely they walke nat after the ſpirite but after the fleſhe. but this holy lybertie admytteth no carnall thynge. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>☞ Of contrycyon. ☜</head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="333"/> COntrycyon is nat a ſorowe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntaryly taken of vs for our ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, but that whiche the ſpirite dothe worke in vs. that is to ſay trewe hate of ſyn, for zele of the glory of god, without hypocryſie or lyenge, for it is a worke alonly of the power of god. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="334"/> ¶ For the wyll of man can nat with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out lyeng and hypocryſy hate ſynne, nor to take for it ſorowe &amp; ſadnes. for the pure wyl of man, which is without the ſpirite of god, is a ſynner alway. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="335"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> God commaundeth that we ſhulde
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:9830:75"/>
take the mournyng of his only ſonne, that is, that we ſhulde be ſorowful and mourne truly for our ſynnes, bycauſe the wyll of a ſynner can nat fulfyll it of it ſelfe. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> For euery precepte of god, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſyble <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="336"/> to the wyll beynge a ſynner, whiche god with hys ſpirite makythe poſſyble to vs. for that whiche he com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundythe in vs he wyll fulfyl in vs, that he alone may haue glorye for all, and that euery fleſhe may nat preſume to be gloryed in hys ſyght.</p>
                  <p>¶ But it is by the hyghe goodnes of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="337"/> god, that he gyueth to his ſeruandes thoſe thyngꝭ that he mercyfully doth in them. callyng them contryte, iuſte, penitent, conuertyd. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>☞ That the preceptes of god be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="338"/> to man this fruyte comyth of it, that man knowing it, is conſtreynid to profeſſe, that he can do nothyng of hym ſelfe, and to meruell at the depnes of the iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gementes of god. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>☞: Of confeſſyon. ☜</head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9830:76"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="339"/> THe maner gyuen of ſcolers for auryculer confeſſyon is vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytable, moſte vayne, inpoſſyble, curyouſe, and moſte dampnable, and aduerſary to the lawe of god, it is ſo muche leſſe that it is of goddꝭ lawe as ſopheſters lye, it is vnprofytable and moſte vayne bycauſe it is without the frute of the ſpirite lettyng fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the purenes of faythe, inpoſſible alſo for innumerable bowes, leaues, mothers, doughters, and cyrcumſtances, which no man althoughe he be lernyd, can di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lygently obſerue, muche leſſe the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lernyd. It is curiouſe alſo, ſerchynge with a friuolouſe care thoſe thynges that be nothyng to the purpoſe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the mynde of him that is confeſſyd is lette that it can nat ryſe with pure faythe in Chriſte, and the ſame confeſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion is to him moſte dampnable, for ſo impure and fylthy thynges be ofte re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>herſyd in ſuche confeſſyons that they corrupte good maners, and infecte as well the ſpeker as the herer. For what be they but euyll comunicacyon, and moſte hurtefull iangelyng, &amp; ſo muche more horryble that they be admyttyd
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:9830:76"/>
vnder the colour of mekenes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> It is the moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſſyd maaſe, what <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="340"/> ſo euer the ſynagoge of the pope, hath gyuen of confeſſyon, vnto this daye, without the worde of god and of hys owne inuencyon. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☜</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> For by what aucthorite, be theſe iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelars <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="341"/> bolde, to preſcribe to the moſte free ſeruauntes of Chriſt, newe lawes ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the doctryne of mekenes.</p>
                  <p>¶ Trewe and profytable confeſſyon <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="342"/> of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes is made foure maner of ways, fyrſte inwardly to god alone. ſeconde openly when cauſe requyreth, thyrde to him whom thou haſte offendyd, leſt thou defende ſynne, but be reconſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd to hym in loue of god. fourthe to him of whom thou lokyſt for the mery worde of the goſpell that is the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of goddes grace and remyſſyon of ſynnes, by Chriſte, and of this laſte we ſpeke. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶ To this thou muſte choſe a propre <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="343"/> confeſſour whom thou ſeeſt able, that he can comforte thy ſpirite with the worde, who ſo euer he be.</p>
                  <p>☞ It is execrable and abhomynable <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="344"/> byfore the lorde, that a faythfull chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyane
<pb facs="tcp:9830:77"/>
is bounde to admytte for a con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſoure and his paſtor, marchauntes and rauenynge wolues, of the kynge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of the ſonne of perdycyon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="345"/> ☞ Therfore thou comynge to a man myghty in the wyſdome and worde of Chriſte, the ſpecyal &amp; that ſame moſte hurtfull ſupputacyon of ſynnes layde aparte, confeſſe moſte purely the to be ſubiecte to many ſynnes, and therfore to haue nede of the marcye of god.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="346"/> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> In the begynnyng therfore, lette him be the moſte meke accuſer of hym ſelfe. the ſeconde let hym beleue ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly in the promyſe of god, that he ſhall gette the grace of god and remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of ſynnes, the thyrde let him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leue that he can haue it, nat by hys owne merytꝭ, or by the merytes of any ſaynte ye of the virgyn mary, but alon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye by the goodnes and meryttes of Chriſt, for he alone is that lambe that takythe away the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes of the worlde, the fourthe that by thys fayth he may be made parttaker of this heuenly iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyce, let him aſcrybe nothyng to the iuſtyce of the fleſhe. but confeſſe with a pure harte alonly the iuſtyce of god
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:9830:77"/>
to be louid, ſerchid for, amplectio, and hym ſelfe to haue of hym ſelfe no iuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyce at all. and knowledge thys with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out feyninge, the fyfthe lette him ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ſome faythfull and conynge man that knowythe to gyue counſell of helthe and with the ſcriptures of god, and can make ſtronge the mynde of the pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nytent in faythe, and if there be nat a man hauyng faythe to do this thynge or he dreadyng him to be vnlawfull, or nat hauyng the worde wherby he may comforthe hym in the lorde. If there be a faythfull woman in who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yth theſe aforſayde to be, to that ſame faythfull woman, ye all though ſhe be ioynyd carnally to hym. I ſaye very nye. It is lawfull for him to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyd generally. I ſay generally that he by no reaſon count hys ſynnes leſt he infecte the herer, for as we haue ſayde euyll comunicacyon corruptyth good maners, and of a truth that ſame foule and lycencyouſe ſpekyng of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyons of antychriſtes factyon haue infecte innumerable and haue drawen them to the moſte enormouſe crymes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Therfore let nothyng be openyd of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="347"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9830:78"/>
any man leſte that for mannes feynyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges &amp; doctryne, he beſeme to dyſpyſe the thynges of god, for god neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dith that, what ſo euer many haue iudgyd in the ſpirite of errour, won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and many punyſhementes be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of certeyne lyers agaynſte them that wyll nat nombre all pertyculerly, but I haue made open that al theſe be of the deuyll in the boke of the cauſes of the blyndenes .&amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="348"/> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The confeſſyon of ſynnes that be longeth to outwarde thynges may be on thys maner. Brother or ſyſter in Chriſte. I perceyue me ouer throwen with infidelite and innumerable ſines, the which I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe with all my herte, I am very iniuſte and full of ifidelite, I haue done no good thynge and am an vnprofitable ſeruande. wherof my ſynnes greatly greue me, and I truely knowe that if I couyt to be ſauyd I had nede of the mercye of god, grace, and iuſtyce, therfore I aſke of you the worde of the goſpell of peaſe, that is to ſaye, remſſyyon of my ſynnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="349"/> ☞ And let euery faythfull take hede that he ſay this thyng without any in fidelyte, and at the laſte lete hym ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:9830:78"/>
beleue that the worde of abſolu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon what ſo euer it be, is a ſure ſigne of the grace of god and remyſſyon of ſynnes as he hathe beleued to be giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him of the lorde. for all the workes of god be in faythe. Pſalm. 32. and euery man taketh ſo muche as he beleuythe, and if he beleue nothyng he receyuith nothynge. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ☜</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>The forme of abſolucyon is free, ſo <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="350"/> that it do ſygnyfie all ſynnes to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myttyd by Chriſte. for this is good, I abſolue the fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thy ſinnes in the name of the father. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. or alonly in the name of Chriſt, or this. I pronounce to the abſolucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all thy ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes in the name &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. or thus thy ſynnes are forgyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the by Chriſte or in the name. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. or thus. By the name of Chriſte al thy ſynnes be forgyuen the. ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶ All ſuche abſolucyon is good, and <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="351"/> to the faythful a ſure ſygne of grace &amp; if he leue out this worde I. It forſyth nat, what ſo euer ſopheſters dreame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The more pure and ſymple the ab<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolucyon <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="352"/> is the better.</p>
                  <p>☞ All abſolucyons of the kyngdome <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="353"/> of the pope be wycked, patching many
<pb facs="tcp:9830:79"/>
thyngꝭ to gyther without frute, of the keys, of the holy mother the churche of the apoſtles Peter and Paule, of ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>comunycacyon more and leſſe frome pena and culpa. ☞ <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="354"/> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> An abſolucyon ought no wyſe to be made in a tonge vnknowen to the penitente. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                     <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="355"/> ☞ For it is neceſſary that he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtande the worde wherby hys ſoule is to be comfortyd in the lorde to whom he muſte nedes beleue.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>¶ Of ſygnes of grace, and remyſſoyn of ſynnes. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="356"/> BAptyſme is to the faythefull as lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge as he lyueth, the moſt ſuriſt ſygne of grace and remyſſyon of ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes, for in al his lyfe he aſking that is moſte aſſurid by that ſigne all though it be receiuyd but ones.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="357"/> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> For what ſo euer the faythful ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyth, as mortyfyeng, cruſyfyeng, quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidiane ſpoylyng of the olde man. be fyguryd in the plongynge out and in the water with the iudgement of the newe man. Roma. 6.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="358"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Another ſygne there is, the table of the lorde, which is to euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:9830:79"/>
it in fayth, the moſte ſuryſt ſigne of grace, and remyſſyon of ſynnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Thys table is a memory of a ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="359"/> ones offerid in the croſſe, and nat the ſacryfyſe.</p>
                  <p>¶ For to affyrme that it is a ſacryfiſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="360"/> and that it ſhulde be ſacryfyed of any man, it is execrable, wicked, and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynable byfore the lorde, and more of this in another place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The thyrde ſygne, is the worde ſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ken <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="361"/> of the churche, or of any faythful, ſygnifieng grace, and remyſſyon of ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes to be gyuen by him that amendith and aſketh it in faythe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Theſe ſygnes be the veſſelles of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="362"/> grace, as manye haue defynyd in the ſpirite of errour.</p>
                  <p>☞ But ſygnes do not brynge grace,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="363"/> but the lorde Pſalmo. 83.</p>
                  <p>It is not gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by ſignes but by fayth <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="364"/>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶ By fayth we be pertakers of al the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="365"/> gyftes of the holye goſte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Alſo theſe ſygnes without faythe / <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="366"/> be nothynge / whiche ſcolers ſaye of fayned thynges, ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> ☞ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>¶ Paule ſaythe Ephe. 5. Chryſt hath <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="367"/> ſantyfyed his churche, made it clene
<pb facs="tcp:9830:80"/>
with the lauer of water, by his worde, verelye it is clenſyd with the worde, when it beleueth it, of the which clen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſynge, the lauer of water is a ſygne, he ſayd not ſymply, it is made clene with the lauer of water, but put to, by the worde, that you maye knowe the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng clene, to be ſygnifyed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lauer.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="368"/> ¶ whiche thou haſte openly. 1. Pe. 3. baptyme hath made vs ſafe, not by the which fylth of the fleſhe, is put away / but it maketh that a good conſcyence, anſweryth well to god, by the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tyon of Ieſus Chryſte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="369"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Althoughe that we get, by the ſame alonlye faythe in Chryſte, grace &amp; full remyſſyon of all our ſynnes, yet god the hyeſt, and greateſte, of the aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of hys goodnes, hathe put to theſe ſygnes, to the greatter comforte of the faythefull.</p>
                  <p>whether any caſes may be reſeruyd <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="370"/> WHat ſo euer the man of ſyn, the ſon of perdycyon, the pope, with all his kyngdome haue reſeruyd and kepte caſes, hath ben a fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge of the deuyl, ſo moch more hate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful, &amp; dampnable, &amp; curſyd, as it repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nethe
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:9830:80"/>
euen contrarye to the eternall ſcryptures of god.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Nothynge at all may be reſerued to <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="371"/> the faythful, that hathe all moſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfully remytted to hym, ſo that there can be no greater.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The church ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nether loſe or bynde <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="372"/> but after the worde of god, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhe muſte be gouerned in all thynge.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Of ſatyſfaccyon, and (as they call it) inioynynge of penaunce.</head>
                  <p>BYcauſe ſatyſfaccyon, for ſynnes dothe ſhewe a ſuffycyencye of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="373"/> deades, by who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euelles be reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, which haue chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyd i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe ſynnes there is no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that can outher gyue or do ſuffycient for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, it is we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyd that ſophyſters thynke, that we can ſatyſfye for them,</p>
                  <p>¶ For nether with faſtynge, prayer,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="374"/> nor almes, or any other worke, we be able to ſatyſfye, bycauſe theſe be not ſatiſfaccions, but frutes of true fayth for there is another ſatyſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, with out all theſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> There is one alone ful, and true ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſfaccyon <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="375"/> for the ſynnes, of all the world, in whom we muſt nedes beleue, made of the lorde Ieſus Chryſte.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:9830:81"/>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="376"/> ¶Sines be ſayde, to be redemed with almes, yf it be of fayth, for they be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demyd of faythe of the gyuer, and not for the almes it ſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="377"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>The ſame iudgement is of faſtynge, and prayer, and of al workes of fayth, which be good bycauſe of true fayth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="378:"/> ¶ whiche fayth beynge abſent, be but mere wekydnes and ſyn, for all that is not of fayth is ſynne. Roma. 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="379"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Of iogelyng ſpirites, and doctryne of deuyls dyd it ſprynge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> many haue affyrmyd penaunce to be inioynyd.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="380"/> ☞For it can not be inioyned of man, but gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god to the ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may truly be penytent for his ſynnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="381"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> They call it folyſhlye penaunce, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theſe chapleyns haue coſtomyd to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyne to him, that telleth his ſynnes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="382"/> ☞ For theyr ought nothynge to be inioyned, by cauſe Chryſte is full ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyſfaccyon, for all faythfull.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="383"/> 
                     <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> The penytent, is to be comfortyd with the worde of god, and to be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſhyd, to true faythe, and the workes of it, for as it is ſayde, what ſo euer is not of faythe, is hypocreſye and ſyn.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="384"/> 
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> Not that people ſhulde be loſyd, or
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:9830:81"/>
that he cleuynge to this maner of con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſyon, ſhulde ſtyke to vs, as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes of antychryſte inioyne vs, but we haue wrytten ſo of penaunce, that al dreames, and lyes of men, put away, and all crafty conueyance, and greate burdens of the kyngedome of anty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chryſte reiecte, Chryſte and the worde of truthe may reygne in euery place.</p>
                  <p>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> we haue ſpoken of penau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, &amp; thoſe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="385"/> that perteyne to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcryptures of god, in fewe wordes, hauynge no regarde, what y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wyked ſynagoge, of the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of antychryſte, in the ſpirite of errour, hath otherwyſe dyffyned, for it is neceſſary for vs, to flye his poyſon, for it can not be, that we ſhal gyue place both to Chryſt, and Antychriſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>
                     <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> The concluſyon.</head>
                  <p>THe ſum of chriſtyanyte we haue breflye wrytten, that is in .385. peradoxes, or poſycyons, that thys boke myght be to bere, in the handes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſyreth it, there was .ij. thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges, that mouyd me cheflye to do it, fyrſte there be very many, that put forthe reprouable peradoxes, as there was one Tregaryus, by whome
<pb facs="tcp:9830:82"/>
they be about to make, the ſymple peo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple ſtraunge, from the truth, the other is that before the .ix. monethe, at the noble cetye of Wetens, the companye of antychryſte, was gatheryd agaynſt me, which mouyd me, to ſtyke vp many poſytyons, verely I put to them a hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and .xxvi. who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue nowe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſyd to .385. let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> anſwere ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore, yf they haue any thynge, let not theſe blynde phareſyes ſtande i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theyr owne conceyte, and legates, and ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes of the ſonne of perdicyon, that for hꝭ decre, and lyke preachynge, dyd make the noble wytnes of Chryſte. S Iohan caſtellane, ſomtyme my welbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louyd brother, the laſte of all that is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 12. daye of the monethe of Ianuarye Anno. 1525. at Vuy a towne of lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therynge, with fyer they made hym a martyr of Chryſte, but for hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god ſhall fyght agaynſte them, and for one well rayſe a thouſande, and yf they hade ſlayne me to, &amp; Chryſt hade vouchſafe thys glorye of martyrdome to me, for me ten thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de ſhulde ryſe, for ſurely antychryſte, with all hys kyngedome apoſtata ſhall falle to the glorye of
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:9830:82"/>
the lorde Ieſus Chryſt, and that with ſpirite of hys mouthe, which with the father, and the holye goſte lyueth one god gloryous, for euer more. So be it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Oo woo be to the thou purple whore / whore of Babylon, that loueth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſygne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roſe coloryd beaſte, and to it empyre, thou arte made drunke with the blode of prophetes, &amp; ſayntꝭ, and dothe call to the ſhedynge of the blode of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> electe, as it were to a feaſt of de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tyes promyſinge to thy aſſyſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, grace, and remyſſyon of ſynnes, with thy falſe iogelynge. woo I ſaye to the for thou ſhalte be dyſtroyd, for with the vyolence of a mylſtone thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen into the ſee, thou ſhalte be ſende into the botome of hel, and thou ſhalt be founde no more Apoca. 18. bycauſe the lorde hathe remembred the blode of hys electe, whom thou haſte ſlayne, and whom thou haſt deceyuyd to eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blyſhe thy lyes, and abhomynatyons, and hathe alwaye trode vnder fode, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> veryte of our lorde Ieſus Chryſte, for
<pb facs="tcp:9830:83"/>
the which thou ſhalt be troden downe of it for euermore, and the beaſte that thou haſte worſhypped ſhall peryſhe with the. So be it.</p>
                  <p>¶ Let thys be done lorde Ieſu, come quyckly, thy enemyes ouercome, and reygne in vs. So be it.</p>
               </div>
               <trailer>The ende of thys collectyon of places of ſcrypture. ☞: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>: ☜ <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g>: <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
                  <g ref="char:trefoil">♣</g> ☞ ☜</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:9830:83"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
